<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Hansard xml:lang="EN" id="13131028">
  <StartPageNumber>1</StartPageNumber>
  <DocumentTitle>
    <DocumentName>EVIDENCE</DocumentName>
  </DocumentTitle>
  <ExtractedInformation>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InstitutionDebate">Standing Committee on Government Operations and Estimates</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Number">NUMBER 003</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Session">1st SESSION</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Parliament">45th PARLIAMENT</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Date">Tuesday, September 23, 2025</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="DateOtherLang">Le mardi 23 septembre 2025</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Institution">Standing Committee on Government Operations and Estimates</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Country">CANADA</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="RecordingNote">[Recorded by Electronic Apparatus]</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="HeaderTitle">EVIDENCE</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="HeaderDate">September 23, 2025</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDocumentCategory">Committee</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaTitle">NUMBER 003</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaTitleEn">NUMBER 003</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaTitleFr">NUMÉRO 003</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaNumberNumber">03</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDateNumDay">23</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDateNumMonth">09</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDateNumYear">2025</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaCreationTime">2025/09/23 11:00:00</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaInstitution">House Of Commons</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InstitutionDebateFr">Comité permanent des opérations gouvernementales et des prévisions budgétaires</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InstitutionDebateEn">Standing Committee on Government Operations and Estimates</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Acronyme">OGGO</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="SpeakerTitle">Chair</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="SpeakerName">Kelly McCauley</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="SessionNumber">1</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="ParliamentNumber">45</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InCameraNote" />
  </ExtractedInformation>
  <HansardBody>
    <OrderOfBusiness>
      <CatchLine />
      <SubjectOfBusiness>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="00">(1100)</Timestamp>
          <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132039">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair (Kelly McCauley (Edmonton West, CPC))</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895858"> I call the meeting to order.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895859">Good morning, everyone. Welcome to meeting three of the House of Commons Standing Committee on Government Operations and Estimates, also known, as the Auditor General calls it, “the mighty OGGO”. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895860"> Before we continue, just as a gentle reminder, everyone, keep your headphones away from your microphones at all times so we can protect the hearing of our very valued interpreters. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895861">Pursuant to Standing Order 108(3)(c), the committee is holding a briefing session with the Auditor General and her team on three reports she tabled, in June 2025, on jet fighter capacity, the use of federal office space, and contracts with GC Strategies. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895862">We now welcome back to OGGO AG Hogan. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895863">Traditionally, we do five minutes, but because there are three reports, feel free to go past the five minutes if you need them. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895864">The floor is yours.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132047">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan (Auditor General of Canada, Office of the Auditor General)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895865"> Thank you. I'll try to be succinct.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895866">Good morning, Mr. Chair. Thank you for the opportunity to appear before the committee today to discuss some of our recent reports that were tabled in Parliament on June 10.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895867"> I would like to begin by acknowledging that we are gathered on the traditional unceded territory of the Algonquin Anishinabe people. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895868">With me today are Andrew Hayes, deputy auditor general, and Nicholas Swales, Markirit Armutlu and Sami Hannoush, the principals who are responsible for the three audits.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895869"> First, our audit of Canada's future fighter jet capability examined the large multi-year project aimed at maintaining a strong fighter jet capability to protect the safety and security of Canadians. We found several risks that could jeopardize the timely introduction of the new CF-35 jets. Estimated costs for the future fighter capability project reached $27.7 billion in 2024, which is almost 50% more than National Defence's original $19 billion estimate, a figure that was based on outdated information. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895870">In addition, estimates did not include key elements, such as infrastructure upgrades and advanced weapons, which would add at least $5.5 billion to the total estimate.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="8895871">Other significant risks include the possibility of a shortage of qualified CF‑35 pilots and a delay of more than three years in the construction of two new fighter squadron facilities. This will require additional costs to build temporary facilities. Active and ongoing risk and cost management is essential to ensure that the CF‑35 fleet is brought into service on schedule.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895872">Let's now turn to our audit of federal office space. As part of this audit, we examined the government's efforts to reduce its office space portfolio to the ideal size in order to lower costs and leverage underutilized space that could be converted to affordable housing. In 2017, Public Services and Procurement Canada estimated that half of federal office space was underutilized.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895873">We found that the department had made little progress in its multi-year effort to reduce office space by 50% by 2034. In particular, efforts between 2019 and 2024 resulted in a reduction of less than 2%, mainly due to a lack of funding. The department estimates that reducing federal office space will result in savings of approximately $3.9 billion over the next 10 years.</ParaText>
              <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="05">(1105)</Timestamp>
              <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="8895874">The Canada Mortgage and Housing Corporation, or CMHC, supported by Housing, Infrastructure and Communities Canada, is tasked with converting surplus federal office properties into affordable housing through the federal lands initiative. The audit found that CMHC is on track to meet the initiative's 2027-28 target of securing commitments to build 4,000 new housing units. However, the target is based only on commitments, and only 49% will be ready for occupancy by 2027-28. Public Services and Procurement Canada and federal tenants must accelerate efforts to help increase stock for housing that is sustainable, accessible and affordable.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895875"> Our last audit examined 106 contracts awarded to GC Strategies Incorporated by 31 federal organizations from April 2015 to March 2024. We found these organizations frequently disregarded government procurement rules meant to ensure fairness, transparency and value for Canadians. </ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="8895876">In 21% of the contracts we reviewed, organizations did not have documentation showing that they had confirmed the security clearances of the individuals performing the work. We also found that organizations often did not monitor the work performed by individuals working under contract. Organizations did not have documentation showing what work had been performed, who had performed it, or whether those individuals had the required experience and qualifications. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895877">These findings echo those of previous audits, which also identified deficiencies in how public servants applied federal procurement rules.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895878">Our report does not contain any recommendations because I do not believe that the federal government needs even more procurement rules. The existing rules must be understood and followed.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895879">Mr. Chair, this concludes my opening statement. We are happy to answer any questions from committee members.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132058">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895880"> Thank you very much, AG Hogan.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895881">We'll start with Mrs. Block for six minutes, please.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132061">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319808" Type="47">Kelly Block (Carlton Trail—Eagle Creek, CPC)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895882">Thank you very much, Ms. Hogan.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895883">Welcome to you and your staff who have joined you in helping us understand the reports that you've tabled. We're talking about fighter jets, we're talking about service contracts and we're talking about federal office space, so there's a wide range of topics that we're covering today.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895884">Getting right to it, your ”Report 3: Current and Future Use of Federal Office Space” says that the Treasury Board plays “a key role” in providing co-operation across government. What, if any, rationale was given for why the Centre of Expertise for Real Property, which was created in 2021, was dissolved only three years later?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132068">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895885"> The Treasury Board Secretariat actually plays many roles when it comes to federal office space. As the employer, they do set the tone for in-office presence. That is a key element to understand when you look at how federal office space is being used and how much is needed.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895886">When it comes to the Centre of Expertise for Real Property, that was put in place to look at a horizontal review of all the fixed assets of the government. It issued 119 recommendations, and we did find that it was dissolved in March 2024. We were told that was because of a lack of funding and that now the responsibility rests with the organizations that had received the recommendations to ensure that the recommendations had been implemented. However, we found that only 21 of the 119 had been implemented by the time the centre was dissolved. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895887">I am concerned that some of those recommendations may be forgotten, but it really now rests with all of the departments that received them to act on them.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="10">(1110)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132071">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319808" Type="47">Kelly Block</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895888"> Thank you.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895889"> According to your report, with this dissolution, the government-wide oversight for implementing recommendations on the government's conversion of the federal lands initiative disappeared, leaving 82% of recommendations not implemented, as you've just pointed out. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895890">Based on your report, had the government kept in place its oversight, do you believe there would have been more progress in their efforts to create affordable housing?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132077">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895891"> I'm not sure that one element of oversight is the thing that would have kept this on track or increased the pace of it. We found in the report that the larger departments that occupy a lot of federal space had not yet signed on for space reduction agreements. They cited to us a lack of clarity around the return-to-office mandate: Would there be an increased presence needed or not, in terms of the space needed to deliver on their mandate? </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895892">There are many elements. While oversight is always a good mechanism to ensure that people stay focused on recommendations and the endgame, I don't think I would say it's the only reason that there's been a lack of progress.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132084">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319808" Type="47">Kelly Block</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895893">Based on your audit, how much would it have cost to keep the oversight program running? I believe they were given $5 million in 2021. How much would it have cost to keep the oversight program running, compared with the cost of delays since its dissolution?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132087">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895894"> I'm not sure I could give you a number. The funding that was received was funding done over three years, and it was meant to do the heavy legwork of doing the whole fixed asset review and then coming up with the recommendation. It would stand to reason that you would need fewer people to continue with oversight. I think the question of what would have been needed to maintain a more consistent level of oversight would be better asked of the Treasury Board. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132094">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319808" Type="47">Kelly Block</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895895"> Did the government provide any rationale for why it did not implement the recommendations on its own?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132102">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895896"> No, I don't think there was one reason. There are 119 recommendations, and it stands to reason that some of them have long lead times.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895897">When you're looking at disposing of underutilized buildings, it's not as though there was a building sitting vacant. They had to figure out which was the best building to be in and consolidate departments and agencies into a building, which meant they had to retrofit or renovate those buildings.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895898">Some of these recommendations have very long tails, so I'm not sure that there would be just one reason that oversight was no longer there.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132112">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319808" Type="47">Kelly Block</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895899"> According to the CMHC, the federal lands initiative gives discounts on the government property purchase based on “the level of social outcomes”.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895900">Did your audit reveal what kinds of discounts federal land is being sold at? If so, what were they?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132120">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895901">We didn't look at what the property was sold for. That wasn't really the focus. Our focus was more on whether the properties were being freed up in locations with the greatest needs for housing. We found that this wasn't always the case. Buildings were being freed up in places where there wasn't the greatest need in a community. That really comes down to Public Services and Procurement Canada having the information to know which buildings it wants to target and then how it moves federal tenants out of them.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895902"> I think our biggest concern was around affordability, meaning the endgame, the outcome. What we found is that the homes being built were really not affordable enough for those most in need.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132124">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319808" Type="47">Kelly Block</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895903"> Thank you very much.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132130">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895904"> Thanks very much.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895905">We'll go to Mr. Gasparro, please.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132137">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319708" Type="47">Vince Gasparro (Eglinton—Lawrence, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895906"> Thank you, Chair.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895907">Thank you for the presentation. It's greatly appreciated. There's a very wide breadth of reports in front of us for sure.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895908">I'm going to focus on the fighter jets, if you don't mind.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895909"> In one of the reports I read, you mentioned the need for training personnel. I think pilots were obviously one of them, but it's personnel more broadly. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895910">Now that the government has committed to increase defence spending to 5% of GDP by 2030, do you have any thoughts on how best to deploy that increase in capital to meet the objectives that you laid out around personnel? That's part one of the question.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895911">Part two is this: Are there any best practices from some of our partners within the program in terms of what they're doing to deploy capital to meet the operational objectives while being as cost-effective as possible?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895912">I'm sorry for the two-part question. I guess I could have broken it up.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="15">(1115)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132142">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895913">That's okay. I wrote them down.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895914">That's a big question, and I'm not sure that we tackled all of that in the fighter jets report. We did look at whether or not there were enough trained pilots, because a concern that my office found in 2018 when we did work on the CF-18s was that there was a shortage of trained pilots.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895915">The finding here, while very similar, highlights that the training program anticipates that it won't have enough qualified pilots. It's a little different here, because you're going to need pilots who can fly both types of aircraft, and then you need to upskill. I know that National Defence is looking at how to adjust that plan, and it's going to need to.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895916">When it comes to my thoughts on where to invest and not invest, and best practices on training, I'm not the one to tell the government where to spend its money. I'm the one who comes in and says, “You made that decision. How did you do in spending it?”</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895917">What I can tell you is that in October we will be releasing a report on training and recruitment of new members to the Canadian Armed Forces. That will speak to some of the concerns that we found there.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895918">There is no shortage of places where National Defence can invest this funding. It's about finding the right place and making sure that you always have the personnel to support that sort of investment. Here you need not only trained pilots, but technicians to maintain the planes and individuals to work on the bases.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895919">There's no shortage of places for DND to invest in.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132148">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319708" Type="47">Vince Gasparro</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895920">That's for sure.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895921">Where I was going with the best practices piece is that there are some examples of our defence partners on this project who have already deployed capital, have deployed resources and have bodies in place. There might be some best practices there. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132153">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895922"> What I would add to that is that Canada is part of the joint strike fighter program office, and in that office, we benefit from what other countries are doing. That office does set minimum standards for the facilities and the training expectations. Canada is benefiting from the best practices of its allies in that program already, but they need to stay focused on it.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895923">One of our findings was really about costing. That program had issued updated costing, yet Canada hadn't been using it in its estimates. Not losing sight of the fact that there is some intel there that we could use would be a good step forward.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132162">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319708" Type="47">Vince Gasparro</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895924"> That's for sure.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895925">How much time do I have, Mr. Chair?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132169">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895926"> You have two minutes.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132177">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319708" Type="47">Vince Gasparro</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895927">I don't know if you're going to have the full time. Maybe on the way back, Mr. Chair, you can follow up. I don't want to completely geek out, but to the eight people who are watching on TV, I hate to put you to sleep, so I apologize in advance.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895928"> I have questions on the methodologies and research you used when coming up with this specific report. What information and data do your office and team researchers rely on? I'm sure it can't be necessarily easy when you're not dealing with fully open-source information, so I'm just curious.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132183">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895929">We have access to a broad range of information that is at times protected and that we can't talk about. I always love talking about audit, so if you really want to geek out on audit, I would encourage you to go to the back of our audit reports, where we have an “about the audit” section. It does list for you our audit criteria.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895930">We follow Canadian auditing standards, which means we have to gather sufficient and appropriate audit evidence. What that might look like will depend on the topic we're auditing, but the expectations that we hold the department to are listed in the back. They're agreed to with the department, and then we look to their information, the databases they may have and the contracts they may have. We will go to other countries to look for examples and other sources. We always try to have criteria that are outside of the federal government to be able to identify gaps and talk about best practices when we can.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895931">It's a little more complicated in the defence space, given that a lot of it is protected, but rest assured that we've seen the information we need to see. It's rigorous enough that you can follow up. You can rely on it.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="20">(1120)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132188">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="245353" Type="28">Andrew Hayes (Deputy Auditor General, Office of the Auditor General)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895932"> I might just add that we do get access to Treasury Board and cabinet documents, so we see the internal analyses that are performed for decision-makers to have the best information possible to make decisions. It is much more than open source. We get pretty much broad access to almost everything. There are very, very small limitations to the information that we can see.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132194">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319708" Type="47">Vince Gasparro</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895933"> That's great. Thank you so much.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132201">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895934"> Thanks very much.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895935">Ms. Gaudreau, go ahead for six minutes, please.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132206">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="40">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau (Laurentides—Labelle, BQ)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895936">Thank you, Mr. Chair.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895937">Ms. Hogan, thank you for your time today. Your contribution to this committee is invaluable. I'm brand new to this committee, but I'm looking forward to getting your next report on recruitment and training in October.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895938">Something struck me when I read your report. I get the sense the government is flying by the seat of its pants. How can it be that departments such as Public Services and Procurement Canada and National Defence lack so much hard data? That's been my first unpleasant surprise since joining this committee. It's quite frustrating.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895939">How can they not know how many federal public servants they need offices for? How are they going to get those numbers? I'd like you to comment on that.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132212">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895940">You're right. We've found that there's not enough data to support informed decisions. There is some data, but it isn't being gathered in a consistent fashion across government. From what we could tell, each department is responsible for figuring out how to monitor its employees' in-office attendance. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895941">We identified the methods used and recommended that the government implement a standardized method to ensure that the whole public service is gathering this data the same way. Once that's done, we'll know how public servants are using office space and decisions can be made about which properties to dispose of.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895942">To sum up, we lack that basic data. There has been progress, but I think a single whole-of-government approach is needed.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132216">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="40">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895943">Mr. Chair, I'd like to ask the Auditor General about the real estate portfolio. It shrank from 6 million square metres in 2019 to 5.9 million square metres in 2024.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895944">Seriously, how is it possible that so little was done in five years?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132221">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895945">We asked that same question. In 2017, the government realized that federal properties were underutilized. In 2019, it decided to cut the amount of office space in half by 2034, but no funding was allocated to that effort between 2019 and 2024.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895946">The 2024 budget allocated money to Public Services and Procurement Canada and Treasury Board to do the work, so I was hoping to see much more progress. The government can make announcements and set targets, but without funding and staff to get it done, very little progress will be made. That's what we're seeing here.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132229">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="40">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895947">According to your report, Public Services and Procurement Canada doesn't know how many public servants are using office space, so it must be hard to manage a portfolio when there's a housing crisis.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895948">I can see the connection to the data. There may have to be a cultural shift to standardize the rules so you can do your work, but, at the same time, when the government makes announcements, it has to walk the talk.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895949">I'd like to talk about F‑35s now. In 2011, when I was the political attaché for the office of the member for Laurentides—Labelle, those jets were a big election issue. That was 14 years ago, and there have been many ministers of defence under Harper, Trudeau and Carney. However, you've told us that the Bagotville and Cold Lake bases are three years behind schedule in building the infrastructure needed to house—just house—fighter jets that cost billions of dollars.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895950">I think being that far behind schedule is hard to fathom.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895951">At what point should we start worrying?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="25">(1125)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132235">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895952">I think it's important to note that National Defence had the right idea. The department decided it would have to upgrade the Bagotville buildings before Canada chose which fighter jet to replace the CF‑18s with, but it didn't have all the details. Once the decision was made to acquire F‑35s, National Defence got a lot more information. Once it realized everything it would need in the buildings, it started falling behind schedule. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895953">There have been efforts to mitigate that, though. There are temporary buildings, but that leads to higher costs. There was a lack of planning and inadequate risk management. We found that risk management was more reactive than proactive. I think this is an example of how the department tried to do the right thing, but, because of reactive risk management, it now finds itself having to use temporary buildings.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132244">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="40">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895954">Thank you, Mr. Chair.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132253">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895955"> Thanks very much.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895956">Mr. Patzer is next. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132259">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319805" Type="47">Jeremy Patzer (Swift Current—Grasslands—Kindersley, CPC)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895957">Thank you very much, Mr. Chair. Thank you very much, everyone, for being here today.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895958">When it comes to the staffing and training, only 14 of the 47 positions have been filled as of 2024. Why is that?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132264">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895959"> I might ask Nick to add some detail to that. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132270">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="190496" Type="28">Nicholas Swales (Principal, Office of the Auditor General)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895960"> I think the point we're making is that implementation has been slow. Part of the reason is that some of the plans had not been fully laid out, so implementation hasn't been advancing at the pace that the plan originally envisaged. That's the main issue in those particular spheres where there were supposed to be a number of positions already filled.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132277">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319805" Type="47">Jeremy Patzer</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895961">If the plan has not been fully implemented, why has it not? </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895962">In the report, I know that you talk about a lack of information back in 2022, but what did you find when you audited this that would have prevented them from getting there? The F-35 has been around for more than 20 years, so how did they not have complete information, and why is a lack of information part of what we're seeing as their reason for not being far enough advanced? </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132284">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895963"> I'll see if Nick does want to add something, but I think your question is bringing in a whole bunch of our findings. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895964">There was information that they didn't use. They used outdated information, which is part of the reason they're a little late. We found that there were a lot of plans that were incomplete, and there was slow progress. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895965">I hope that our audit in October on recruitment might shed some light on progress and weaknesses in recruiting, but logistics and security positions are some of the areas they need to plan to recruit for. I think there's a lot to figure out here in why they've been making slow progress. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895966">I don't know if you want to add at all, Nick.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132291">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319805" Type="47">Jeremy Patzer</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895967"> I want to jump in right there. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895968">In your report, you say there are 246 permanent positions required. In the report, there are 10 bases that are on the map. I know most of the report is based on Bagotville and Cold Lake. It seems to me that 246 permanent staff for those 10 bases would be a massive understaffing of what would be required for the F-35 program. I'm not an expert, but are the 246 positions just for the first two bases, or is that for all 10 bases? What is that for?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132297">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="190496" Type="28">Nicholas Swales</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895969"> Mr. Chair, perhaps I can help to explain that. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895970">One of the observations we make is that the process of implementing the F-35 transition is in its early stages, and the plans haven't been fully drafted. This was one area where there was a plan that had laid out how many positions they actually needed in specific areas. We specify that it was for mission planning and some types of logistics and security. That is not the entire need for the F-35 program on all those bases. That was simply those areas where they had actually identified a number of positions by a certain time period, and only a small number of those had so far been filled. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895971">For the rest, there wasn't that level of detail in the plans yet. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="30">(1130)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132301">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319805" Type="47">Jeremy Patzer</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895972"> Why is that level of detail not in the plans yet? I guess that's kind of what I'm trying to get at here. This has been ongoing for years, yet we still have an incomplete plan. Why is that? Who's responsible for this? Do you have a name for who hasn't completed the planning for this? It is kind of crazy that we don't have a complete plan yet. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132307">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895973"> Mr. Chair, I think I would send the member to exhibit 2.2. We outlined the five phases of transitioning from the CF-18s to the CF-35s, and they're still in phase 1. The buildup phase is coming. This is National Defence's plan. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895974">Ultimately, who is responsible? The chief of the defence staff and the deputy minister are, ultimately. Making sure that Canada's fighter jet capability is available and can transition is their ultimate responsibility. I think those are the questions that should go to National Defence—questions about progress, about the gaps in their plans and about how they plan on updating them. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895975">We did give them a recommendation about making sure that their master plan was much more comprehensive.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132312">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895976"> Thank you Mr. Patzer.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895977">Ms. Rochefort, go ahead, please, for five minutes. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132316">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319706" Type="47">Pauline Rochefort (Nipissing—Timiskaming, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895978">Good morning, Ms. Hogan.</ParaText>
              <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
              <ParaText id="8895979"> Mr. Chair, is it for five minutes or six? </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895980">
                <B>The Chair:</B> You have five minutes.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895981">
                <B>Pauline Rochefort:</B> Thank you. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895982">Thank you for highlighting the fact that Public Services and Procurement Canada was provided funding in 2024-25. Basically, if I understand correctly from your report, there's a first tranche of 37 tenants, representing 90% of the office space, who were asked to begin reducing their office space in June 2024, so that's just about a year. Of those, you said that 15 of them had not yet signed an office space reduction agreement and that negotiations were still ongoing at the time of the audit. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895983">Is that normal? How would you characterize the fact that not all of the 37 tenants representing such a major component of the office space had not yet signed an agreement? Could you share the names of those tenants?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132321">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895984"> I don't know the names of all 15. We would have to look into our files and see if we could get back to the committee.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895985"> I do believe that you could ask Public Services and Procurement Canada. That is the best way to get the most accurate information. Ours was from the point in time when we did the audit, which was several months ago, and I would hope that there would be progress. My advice would be to get that information from them.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895986">Why had 15 out of the 37 not yet signed agreements? We heard a few things. One, as I mentioned earlier, was about the uncertainty around the return-to-office mandate and whether they would need more space than what they anticipated they could occupy. Some said that the space was needed to properly deliver on their mandate.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895987">Another would be perhaps the lack of a financial incentive. Many federal organizations do not pay rent. We occupy space that Public Services and Procurement Canada has; for example, my office doesn't pay rent. It then becomes the will of the deputy minister to put up their hand. I have, and I have offered to reduce the space in Ottawa by almost 50%, even though I don't have a financial incentive. That might also be part of the reason that certain departments are not putting this on their priority list.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132325">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319706" Type="47">Pauline Rochefort</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895988"> Would “uncertainty” be correct?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132333">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895989"> It's uncertainty, and there are really so many things to focus efforts on. This isn't something that's costing you something, but it is costing the bigger, broader federal government. I think every department should look at how they can contribute to meeting this goal.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132338">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319706" Type="47">Pauline Rochefort</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895990"> You mentioned in your report a resistance to change. Was that an equally significant factor?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132345">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895991">They were all factors of varying degrees. It depends on the department. For example, some might have had dedicated individual office spaces for each employee, so the resistance to change there would have been much greater than if they were already in an environment where they were hotelling and they would just reserve a spot and sit there. It's a big transition for many public servants as well. There are many factors that play into why progress is slow.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="35">(1135)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132352">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319706" Type="47">Pauline Rochefort</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895992">You also, as part of your audit, did a survey yourself. Is that correct? Not all tenants responded. Is that a surprise? Normally, with this form of survey, do they all—</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132362">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895993">I have to admit that I was impressed with the response rate. Getting an over 80% response rate on a survey is considered extraordinary and is actually a really good result. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895994">Those were their thoughts and views, and that's why we felt confident enough to put them in our audit report. It wasn't like a handful had reported; the majority really had given us their views.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132366">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319706" Type="47">Pauline Rochefort</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895995"> Thank you very much.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132374">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895996"> Ms. Gaudreau, go ahead for two and a half minutes, please.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132380">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="40">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8895997">Mr. Chair, I'd like to use my two and a half minutes to ask the Auditor General a question.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895998">I read in your report that Public Services and Procurement Canada did not release the information you said you needed. That worries me. I'm worried things will stagnate, the House will just rubber-stamp things and we'll sacrifice more and more transparency in all the legislative work we do in favour of doing things as quickly as possible and reacting to economic conditions.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8895999">Have you observed such a trend in your work with the government, or does this reflect what MPs are experiencing these days?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132385">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896000">That's a big question.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896001">In many cases, departments are reluctant to release information they haven't yet examined because they don't want surprises.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896002">Our audit of current and future use of federal office space found that some data should have been made public. That would really have been more in line with best practices.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896003">We talked about Australia's practices with respect to data about office occupancy and the fact that, in my opinion, if Canada followed such practices, that would help deputy ministers decide whether to dispose of certain premises. That's what we were getting at.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896004">Overall, I believe some data should sometimes be made public. That's why we identified that data in our reports to ensure good conversations happen and the information needed to support good decision-making is made public. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132392">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="40">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896005">Overall, I get very concerned when I hear about the government being reactive rather than proactive. I'm an entrepreneur, and if I operated that way, my businesses would fail. This is worrisome.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132398">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896006">Risk management has to use both approaches, but I expect to see more proactive mitigation measures, with reactive measures as needed, not the other way around.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132407">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="40">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896007">Thank you.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132414">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896008"> That's a very good point.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896009">Next we'll go to Ms. Jansen, please, for five minutes.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132418">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319807" Type="47">Tamara Jansen (Cloverdale—Langley City, CPC)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896010">Thank you so much for coming. Thank you for the reports you've done.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896011">I'm hoping to focus on the current and future use of office space. I'm trying to better understand how the affordable housing programs work, because when I talk to families in my constituency, I find that they don't really care about the big announcements in Ottawa; they care about whether they can actually pay the rent and get an affordable roof over their heads.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896012">I noticed in the report that Ottawa uses the term “affordable housing” to mean 80% of today's sky-high market rent, and StatsCan says that it should be no more than 30% of a family's income. Those two radically different definitions seem to me to be a bit of a problem. Would you agree that this difference in definitions is a big part of the problem and exactly why the lowest-income families, the ones we need to help the most, are still being left out in the cold?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132423">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896013">On the concern around the measure used for affordable housing, it's not the first time that I've raised this concern. I did an audit on chronic homelessness and identified.... As you say, Statistics Canada bases affordable housing on rent, but so does the national housing strategy. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896014">Canada's national housing strategy says that this is the benchmark: You shouldn't spend more than 30% of pre-tax household income on your housing needs. However, the Canada Mortgage and Housing Corporation, which delivers many of these programs, uses a different one. They do base it, in this program and in a few others, on 80% of median market rent. At a time when rent is increasing because of the shortage of housing, we end up with rental properties that are not meeting the needs of those who need them the most. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896015">In this case, there was that definition, but there's also the fact that the buildings that were being released to be used in the federal lands initiative were not in cities with the greatest need, so there were two things at play here that we think could increase access to affordable housing.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="40">(1140)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132430">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319807" Type="47">Tamara Jansen</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896016">Does it make sense to you that the new $13-billion Build Canada Homes program is using the exact same flawed affordability definition as was used in the federal lands initiative? If the smaller program failed to deliver real affordability, why should Canadians expect that this much bigger program won't just fail on a much bigger scale?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132436">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896017">I'm sorry. I can't really talk about that program. What I would expect a housing program to look at would be affordability and accessibility, and also sustainability. There's a trade-off among them. Not every home can meet all of those criteria. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896018">I would also like to see homes built along the spectrum of houses, not just rental properties. There are other types of housing along the housing spectrum that I would expect a housing program to consider in terms of the costs and benefits in where you invest in a given year.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132440">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319807" Type="47">Tamara Jansen</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896019"> I thought that maybe we could just talk about Canadians who are currently struggling to make ends meet, such as the store manager at a grocery chain. Maybe they're earning about $50,000 a year. Under Ottawa's definition, their affordable rent in Vancouver could still be $2,500 a month. That's over half of their paycheque. How would a single mom working full time make that work?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132448">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896020">While I love math, I'm not the one who can help someone manage their day-to-day budget. I think it's important to note that the national housing strategy does call for affordability to be based on household income, and that the Canada Mortgage and Housing Corporation is using a different definition. In both of the reports I mentioned—the chronic homelessness one and this one—we have given a recommendation to the Canada Mortgage and Housing Corporation to relook at that, and I would expect that they would align with what's in the national housing strategy at some point.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132457">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319807" Type="47">Tamara Jansen</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896021"> When government calls these units “affordable”, isn't it true that most of the vulnerable families in our communities—single parents, one-income families—still won't be able to afford them? </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132465">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896022"> I would state that they are more affordable in that they're less than market rent, but they aren't meeting those with the greatest needs. Something a government should be concerned about is helping those who are furthest behind and moving them forward first. That's why I would expect that when you determine affordability, some of the houses would be based on income threshold.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132473">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319807" Type="47">Tamara Jansen</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896023">I actually had one more example, because I want Canadians to understand what this really means. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896024">Let's say there's a single-income family, with a dad working as a long-term care worker, which is also 50,000 bucks a year, and he's paying $2,500 in rent. That basically leaves him $1,700 to cover gas, groceries, heat and clothes for the kids. The rent that they're paying is not actually affordable. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896025">Would you agree?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132479">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896026">Provide a very brief answer, if you're able to.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132487">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896027">Again, I would point to Statistics Canada and the national housing strategy's definition that affordability, when it comes to housing, should be based on pre-tax income and should consider all the other things that a household has to spend on.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132495">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896028">Thanks very much. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896029">We're going to go to Mr. Gaheer. Go ahead for five minutes, please.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132502">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321015" Type="40">Iqwinder Gaheer (Mississauga—Malton, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896030"> Thank you, Chair, and thank you to the AG for appearing before committee. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896031">Ma'am, you talked about challenges regarding the CF-35 program, including a lack of integrated planning and coordination, insufficient infrastructure readiness, and gaps in workforce and recruiting. We know that having a modern, agile and effective fighter jet fleet is key to Canada's defence of its airspace and of North American airspace. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896032">As we make the strategic investment away from the existing CF-18 fighter jets to a new fleet, what factors must be taken into account to reduce operational capability gaps and reliance on our partners? </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="45">(1145)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132511">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896033"> I'm going to see if Nick will want to jump in on that. That's a bigger, broader question about having the military ready. This audit was really focused in on the transition between the CF-18s and the CF-35s. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896034">I think we identified the need to make sure that estimates and costing use the most up-to-date information and that it's recognized that those need to be evergreen. Things keep going.... </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896035">For many of the cost increases here, some are within control of the Department of National Defence and some are outside the control of the Department of National Defence, such as inflation, the global demand for munitions and foreign exchange. When a decision is made, those all have to be factored in up front. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896036">However, it's not just about having equipment and infrastructure. It's making sure that you have the personnel to man them. We can have all 88 CF-35s, but we need trained pilots and we need trained technicians to maintain them so that in the long term we can have a strong fighter jet capability for the country. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896037">National Defence has a lot of balls to manage. I think your question is best asked of them on how they plan to do that going forward.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132519">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321015" Type="40">Iqwinder Gaheer</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896038"> Could you talk about the costing controls that are within the department's control? You said some are outside its control and some are within its control. What's within its control? </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132526">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896039">When it originally announced that Canada was moving to CF-35s, the estimate was that the project would cost $19 billion. In my view, what is in the control of the department is that this information was based on outdated information. There were already up-to-date cost estimates for what a fighter jet would cost. They hadn't been factored in. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896040">They also didn't include in that project all of the elements needed to make sure that the planes could reach their full operational capability, meaning that they could be used as intended. Some of the things that were missing were power grid upgrades in some of the infrastructure that was essential, and also some of the advanced weaponry. You needed to have missiles on those fighter jets if you wanted to use them as intended, and they weren't there. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896041">This is why we say the cost estimates now are at $27.7. billion. There are at least another $5.5 billion that should be added to that in order to look at the cost of fully transitioning from CF-18s to CF-35s.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132536">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321015" Type="40">Iqwinder Gaheer</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896042"> I haven't looked at the contracts, obviously. When these contracts are negotiated, I'm assuming from what you're saying that it's not a fixed price—like, if you want to buy one jet, this is the cost that it's going to be. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896043">Is that usual practice for how these contracts are negotiated? </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132542">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896044">In this case, it isn't a contract. There's a memorandum of understanding with the United States. This is a nation-to-nation agreement. Canada is part of a group of allies that are purchasing CF-35s.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896045"> Canada's memorandum of understanding calls for 88 planes to be delivered to Canada. That's why Canada is part of the joint strike fighter program office. It's so they can keep on top of the cost and the latest upgrades that are needed in buildings and so on. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896046">This is unique. It's not like entering into a contract to buy 88 cars; this is about having fighter planes that are compatible with those of our allies.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132549">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321015" Type="40">Iqwinder Gaheer</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896047"> I think it's obviously very dynamic in that sense, but how should the Royal Canadian Air Force then balance the operational needs and requirements they have with the budget and options that are available?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132553">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896048"> This is where we called for better transparency around the full costs of the project and more regular updates, and those were some of the recommendations we put in our report.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132560">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321015" Type="40">Iqwinder Gaheer</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896049">We know it's also very important that Canada has fully operational main operating bases where the fighter jets can be stationed and where they can conduct day-to-day operations and training. Can you tell us anything about the upgrades or changes that will need to be made to existing operating bases as Canada procures the new fighter jets? You've talked about it very briefly.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132566">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896050">I'm sorry. We're past our time, but you can offer a brief answer.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132568">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896051">Yes, I can offer a really brief answer. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896052">What we've put in here about power upgrades and making sure the facilities are available is the extent to which we can talk about that. The rest of that is information we can't put in the public domain.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="50">(1150)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13134043">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321015" Type="47">Iqwinder Gaheer</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896053">Thank you.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132575">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896054"> Thank you, Mr. Gaheer.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896055">We'll now go to Mr. Gill. Go ahead for five minutes, please.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132580">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319809" Type="2">Harb Gill (Windsor West, CPC)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896056"> Thank you, Mr. Chair. Thanks for joining us, folks.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896057"> I'm going to talk about GC Strategies a bit. You said that in 21% of the contracts you examined, you found the federal organizations lacked documentation on file that showed valid security clearances for contract resources. The question I have is this: Did you find any evidence of citizens' personal or health information being compromised, or the possibility of that occurring?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132586">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896058"> Our finding really is flagging the risk that it could occur. When you don't have the right security clearances on file and you haven't checked that, there is a risk that personal information, government information or government assets could be exposed when they shouldn't be.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896059"> We did, however, look at some of the contracts. We didn't look at all of them in detail and we didn't find any breaches. Not having the information on file doesn't mean the person didn't have a security clearance; it means it wasn't there.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896060">We also looked at this in ArriveCAN and didn't find breaches, but this is a risk. If you determined that a contractor should have security clearance, they should not be doing the work until they have that security clearance.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132589">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319809" Type="2">Harb Gill</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896061">That's true.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896062"> The next question I have, ma'am, is this: Canadians expect the federal organizations to have controls, processes and policies in place to support fair, open and transparent procurements and to promote value for money. As regular Canadians are asking, are we getting value for our money?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132593">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896063"> I'm always asked that question. At times that's a very easy answer to give, and at other times it's a more complex answer to give.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896064"> When we were looking at the contracts with GC Strategies, we saw that at times they were to provide advice or a report, and we saw those reports, but at other times there was no evidence as to what work was done. When we spoke with public servants, they told us that there had been a lot of work and they assured us that they had received value for money, but what was missing was the ability to demonstrate that to us.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896065">That's why we've called for going back to basics here. It's not about creating more rules; it's about understanding the rules that are there, knowing why they should be implemented and then implementing them. Making sure the government received what they contracted for before authorizing payment is basic, and often we saw that this wasn't happening.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132598">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319809" Type="2">Harb Gill</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896066"> Based on that, if the work was not completed and the payment was still made, has any department or agency tried to recover the money that was paid to GC Strategies for work that was not completed but for which payment was made?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132603">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896067"> I'm often asked this question as well.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896068"> The difficulty there is that one of the final steps a public servant should do is to certify, before saying to go ahead and make the payment, that the goods or services were received. We saw consistently that public servants were certifying that; what we were looking for was proof.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896069">For example, 94% of the contracts we looked at required time sheets in order to demonstrate that a contractor had done work. We found that those were very rarely there. In almost 60% of the cases, there was little to no evidence of that. In fact, in one contract, there was only one contractor out of 25 who had a time sheet. That doesn't mean the work wasn't done; it means there's no ability to demonstrate to Canadians that you received value for money. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896070">That's a big gap and a big hole that shouldn't be there. It's not as easy as saying that because you didn't have a time sheet, nothing was done, and you should go recover the money; it's about knowing whether or not the work was done.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132607">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319809" Type="2">Harb Gill</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896071"> You note that you're not making any recommendations with this report, as you had already made them before, and you reconfirm that the policy should be well understood by now by these various agencies. I'm sensing a degree of exasperation on your part, because you go on to say that the procurement policies in place as of 2024 “promote fairness, transparency and value for Canadians—when they are followed.” </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896072">In that regard, what is the percentage of compliance to federal policies across the various departments and agencies? Second, who is the most compliant, and perhaps who is the least compliant?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132610">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896073"> I'm not sure I could give you that answer. I would have to point you to a few reports that we did. We did a report on professional services contracts that looked at work awarded to McKinsey. There was this work on contracts awarded to GC Strategies. This report had 31 federal entities in it. The other one had 20. In almost every case, there was something that was missing. This included federal Crown corporations, departments and agencies. That's why I think there is a need to take a step back and ask why this is happening. Are there too many procurement rules, so individuals just don't know them all and it's impossible to apply them all, or is it that they're working around them? </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896074">I think that that's what the government has to find out, which is why I didn't want to contribute to more rules. I think you have to go back to the basics. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="55">(1155)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132617">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896075">Thank you very much. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896076">Mr. Sousa, welcome back to OGGO. You went a whole week without appearing here. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896077">Go ahead, sir. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132621">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa (Mississauga—Lakeshore, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896078"> It's a pleasure, Chair.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896079">Thank you, Auditor General, for your report. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896080">Believe us, we value the contributions you make in regard to all these reviews and recommendations and in highlighting some of the issues that we always need to be apprised of. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896081">Let's start with GC Strategies. I know that PSPC had already implemented a host of changes. There's much that you have done and much that the ombudsman has done over the course of the last two years: improving the guidance of other government departments, putting caps on task-based contracts, mandatory value-for-money assessments for all RFPs with a time-based basis for payment, mandatory reporting by client departments for the usage of mandatory methods of supply, and ADM-level approval for non-competitive contract extensions and single-bid procurements. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896082">Auditor General, does that demonstrate to you that other federal contractors should be mindful of the rules? You've made it clear that we don't need any more rules; we just need to abide by them. This happened during the pandemic period. What's happening now, relative to some of these issues?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132626">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896083"> I'm going to talk about two reports, the one on GC strategies and then the one on professional services with McKinsey. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896084">Both of those reports went back in time. In this case, we looked at contracts from 2015 to 2024: prior to the pandemic, during the pandemic and postpandemic, if we're in a postpandemic time. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896085">This is pervasive, and that's why to me it isn't just about what happened since you've changed the rules. All of the rules that were changed were changed following some of my work, so this is forward-looking. All I can tell you is that in the past, there was a rather pervasive lack of respect for rules, which is why going back to training and reinforcing what they are is the first step. It's not creating more rules. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132631">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896086">To be clear, your recommendations, the ombud's recommendations and some of the other reports and investigations that were provided have been adopted by government. We have taken, if I understand correctly, all of these things into action, recognizing some of the things that may have been amiss previously. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896087">Was there any interference or engagement by elected officials in any of these contracts? </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132635">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896088">There was engagement in one contract, I do recall, with an elected official, but that was required by procurement rules because of the dollar value of the contract. Other than that, this is work done by the public service that we are looking at. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896089">I would like to think that returning to the basics and re-educating people will help procurement going forward, but I do think that there are a lot of rules, and there is a need to decide whether streamlining them will bring better efficiency and better value for money.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132640">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896090">During the time of the pandemic, there was an acceleration in trying to get things done very quickly under the urgency of the time. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896091"> On another matter, the F-35s, are you called before PACP as a witness on this very issue? You're here today. Are you doing more committees?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132646">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896092"> This afternoon I'm going to the public accounts committee, but that's for an in camera discussion about my office and how we can support committee members. Any time I'm invited, I'm more than happy to go to a committee. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896093">Typically, the national defence committee and the Senate committee would study this. I would trust that the public accounts committee will have outlined what they're expecting to study, perhaps after they chat with me this afternoon.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132652">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896094">Would it be appropriate, given the recommendations and the work and the reports you've made...? It's now been given to government for their review. Are they reviewing it? I believe there is a review under way right now by government to respond to some of the work you've done. Is that correct?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="00">(1200)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132658">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896095"> I believe that the <Affiliation DbId="314774" Type="1">Prime Minister</Affiliation> asked for a review of the decision to purchase the F-35s. That has not yet been made public. Other than that, the departments have responded to our recommendations, and they've agreed with them. It is now really up to the public accounts committee and other committees to hold them to account for delivering on the action plans they intend to use.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132663">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896096">Thank you.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896097">Would it be appropriate to have those action plans before us in response? You're going to go before these committees and you're going to talk about the issues that you've already reported, but the main question from all of us is, what's going to happen next? That's the report we're waiting for.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132670">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896098">The public accounts committee does require that every department that is in a report submit a detailed action plan to them. I would imagine that, committee to committee, you could get hold of that, or you could ask National Defence for their action plan to use as part of your study on these reports.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132675">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896099">I understand.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896100">Do I have any time left?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896101">I do not.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132682">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896102">There will be plenty of time afterward, though.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896103">Go ahead, Ms. Gaudreau, please.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132688">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="40">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896104">I have a question about National Defence as well.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896105">Over the past few weeks, we've been hearing a lot about how the government is planning massive spending. We'll find out on November 4.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896106">On June 25, the <Affiliation DbId="314774" Type="1">Prime Minister, Mr. Carney</Affiliation>, told NATO that Canada would allocate up to 5% of its GDP to military spending.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896107">That's all well and good, but we heard earlier that there's a shortage of pilots and technicians. National Defence is unable to spend its money at this point.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896108">Are we on the right track? Is that pledge to increase Canada's military spending to 5% of its GDP realistic?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132693">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896109">That's a hard question for me to answer because I don't know exactly how the government plans to spend the money it has allocated.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896110">I know some of the money will go to a pay increase for National Defence personnel, and I think that will help with recruitment and retention. I can't say any more than that about whether Canada is on the right track or not. I would have to see what decisions the public service makes. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132700">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="40">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896111">My last question is about accountability and transparency. As I said, I worked in a certain field.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896112">How can it be that the government is unable to demonstrate what it has to do in terms of accountability when many small organizations, including many not-for-profits, have to undergo reviews and audits before they can get a contract or funding? Those organizations don't even have the internal expertise to do that.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896113">How can it be that the government awarded 106 contracts through GC Strategies without even checking security clearances, without following the rules and without appropriate accountability, just because it said the situation was urgent?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896114">I expect the rules to be very clear, and I expect all departments to follow them. I also expect to see direct communication between you and the departments, and I expect you to have all the information you need to do your job properly.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132706">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896115"> You've mentioned the precise reason why I did not make any recommendations in the report on GC Strategies. There are already many rules governing procurement. It's time to take a step back to ensure that there are not too many, that we keep the ones that are necessary, and that we then ensure that they are properly implemented.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132710">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="40">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896116">Thank you very much, Mr. Chair. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132716">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896117"> Mrs. Block is next.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132722">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319808" Type="47">Kelly Block</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896118"> Thank you, Chair.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896119"> I want to circle back to some of the questions that my colleague was asking in regard to CMHC. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896120">According to your report, you found that under the federal lands initiative, CMHC was reporting numbers that were already committed under another agreement as their own. Is it possible that, outside the scope of your audit, there are other instances of numbers being reported like this?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="05">(1205)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132728">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896121"> You're right about this report. We highlighted what I would say is a lack of clarity in their reporting. CMHC is still leading other projects, but those homes were counted in another project and then counted again here because land was added to the projects through the lands initiative. While that might be how you want to get to your 4,000 commitments, I think you just need to be clear. That's why we made some recommendations around a project being delayed and so on. That kind of information is useful.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896122"> My biggest concern in this area is around how they're measuring success. They're measuring success based on commitments, which is a great benchmark to get to, but those buildings are not ready for occupancy, and people who need affordable housing are going to be waiting longer than 2027 or 2028 to be able to move in.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132733">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319808" Type="47">Kelly Block</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896123"> Thank you. I agree with you. I know the government has made very ambitious commitments to tackle housing affordability, including with the federal lands initiative. After making those commitments, how you get there matters, so I appreciate what you pointed out in this report.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896124"> I think you mentioned this already. CMHC was also found to be reporting units committed and units that have been built in the same category, as we just discussed. You noted that after examining all 23 agreements, you found that they provided for only half of that—49%, I think. You spoke to it not being 4,000.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896125"> Could this be misleading to Canadians looking to evaluate the government's progress on the commitments that we just spoke about?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132741">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896126"> I think your question aligns exactly with the statements I was making about providing better clarity. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896127">We did conclude that they're well on track. I'm just trying to find the exhibit number that I can give you. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896128">Exhibit 3.3 in the report outlines our lay of the land. The 49% is really those that will be available for occupancy by 2027-28, even though they're well on track to meeting the benchmark of having commitments for 4,000. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896129">As everyone knows, when you do a renovation or a build, there are things that cause delays. Even that kind of clarity could be provided so that there is more accurate information for Canadians to make decisions on where they could access affordable housing.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132744">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319808" Type="47">Kelly Block</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896130"> Thank you very much. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896131">Mr. Chair, how much time do I have?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132751">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896132"> You have a minute and a half.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132764">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319808" Type="47">Kelly Block</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896133">I have one final question.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896134">In your report, there were groups having difficulties navigating “the CMHC's legal framework”.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896135">For indigenous businesses and for smaller and medium-sized businesses, what options do they have to participate in programs like these without having to hire lawyers, consultants or lobbyists? How do they compete?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132772">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896136"> I will see if Markirit wants to add anything here, but I will offer this. We spoke with indigenous groups, and they actually appreciated their experience through the federal lands initiative and are eager to participate again. However, they did raise concerns with us about the burden that it puts on an indigenous community to deal with all of the paperwork, the process and so on.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896137"> That's where I would expect the federal government, in the spirit of true reconciliation, to support indigenous communities who want to participate, supporting them differently from the way they would support another builder in the country. It's about figuring out what they need, meeting them halfway and supporting them better. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896138">I don't know if there's anything you want to add, Markirit. It's not necessary. It's up to you.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13142525">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896139">Briefly—</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132797">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319808" Type="47">Kelly Block</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896140">Okay. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896141">Could you comment as well on the experience of the small and medium-sized businesses that would want to compete in that space?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132804">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896142"> I don't know if we zeroed in on smaller businesses versus larger businesses, but there are only 23 agreements, so there are not many participating. I think you need rigour no matter what, but you can't make it too much. That would be the advice I'd offer. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="10">(1210)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132811">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896143">Thanks very much.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896144">Mr. Gasparro, please go ahead for five minutes. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132822">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319708" Type="47">Vince Gasparro</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896145">Thank you, Mr. Chair.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896146"> I'm glad you just mentioned that housing and infrastructure more broadly do take time to build and to develop. On that point, you noted in the report, on page 15, that the federal lands initiative is on track to meet its goals. Are there any positive lessons the government should be taking as they go about setting up the Build Canada Homes program?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132836">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896147">I think it would be in setting up the right measurement. You succeed because you stay focused on what you're going to measure, and measuring commitments is not the outcome needed. They're well on track for the commitments. Wouldn't it have been so much more exciting to say, “well on track for having occupancy” by those years? </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896148">I would say that the lesson is this: They did a great job at setting a metric, one that focuses on outcomes as well as the midpoint should be there. A commitment is a great midpoint, but then the outcome is one I would hope they would focus on. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896149">Here, Public Services and Procurement Canada is trying to pilot accelerated ways of disposing of buildings, and I think it's a good lesson learned to see how that pilot is going. There were 10 buildings that were put into that to shorten the period of time. Usually it takes about eight years to free up a building and move it into the lands initiative, and they're trying to do it in three. Building on some of their lessons learned throughout the pandemic—doing things not sequentially but together—could speed up the process. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896150">It was too early for us to tell whether or not that will materialize, so I'd like to see them focus in on that, on better ways to free up buildings and get them into the federal lands initiative.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132848">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319708" Type="47">Vince Gasparro</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896151">For sure, I think occupancy and infrastructure projects going into certificate of occupancy are incredibly important, but you have to be going through the process at a timely clip in order to get to that final occupancy and that ultimate result that we all want. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896152">In addition, do you have any overall thoughts on how the government should be going about streamlining the federal lands initiative, which you touched on a little, and public lands programs under the Build Canada Homes program?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132858">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896153">The overall thought I would give is that when you make a commitment, it sets out expectations, and then with expectation comes the need to be transparent in progress and in how you plan on getting there. As the government moves through more home initiatives, I would encourage being clear and transparent about where projects are.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132866">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319708" Type="47">Vince Gasparro</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896154"> That's great. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132873">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896155">We will now go to Mr. Patzer for five minutes. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132883">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319805" Type="47">Jeremy Patzer</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896156">The cost overruns on the F-35s right now are at $27.7 billion in total, so it's definitely over budget with a 50% increase. The $7-billion defence of Canada fighter infrastructure project is above and beyond that $27.7 billion. Is that correct?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132894">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896157"> Yes, that's correct, and I think it's important to note that the $27.7-billion estimate is National Defence's estimate. We believe another $5.5 billion should be added to that for some essential weapons and for facility upgrades. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132905">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319805" Type="47">Jeremy Patzer</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896158">If DND's estimate, which by extension means your audit, was based on incomplete information, how much more do you think the cost overrun actually is?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132919">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896159">Well, it is at least $5.5 billion more than the $27.7 billion. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896160">We did try to sit back and ask, “What does make a CF-35 fully operational and capable?”, and that's why we picked up certain other elements. Other things that we couldn't cost yet, because the government hadn't costed those, would have been the interim facilities that are needed because of the three-year delay in the two main bases. They do need to have interim facilities, and that hadn't been costed out yet, so that would need to be added as well. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896161">That's why we recommended a much more active and, at minimum, annual process in monitoring costs and updating estimates so that DND knows what it needs to commit going forward. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="15">(1215)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132929">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319805" Type="47">Jeremy Patzer</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896162"> Did you get a sense of the actual final number of full-time employees that would be required? I know the report says 246, but you said that this number was based on a certain level of completeness of the program. I'm assuming that's Cold Lake and Bagotville. It wasn't based on the full completeness of the program. There are also the other eight bases that are listed in your report, particularly Inuvik and Iqaluit. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896163">When this program is fully rolled out and fully implemented, how many full-time employees are we going to need above and beyond that 246? Do you know?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132935">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896164">As we mentioned in the report, the 246 are about planning, logistics and security. There's so much more that goes into running a base. You would have to add in pilots, technicians and maintenance crew. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896165">I don't have that number, and neither does National Defence right now. They haven't finished all of their plans, which is why we could only talk to you about the level of detail that we have here.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896166">We do know that they're planning for pilot training. Their current plans don't envision having enough pilots, so they need to do something different to ensure that they are ready when those aircraft arrive in Canada.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132944">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319805" Type="47">Jeremy Patzer</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896167"> The first group of pilots are being trained in the United States. Is that correct?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132952">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896168">That's correct.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896169">The first few aircraft are going to the United States. They're expected to be there in 2026 to train Canada's pilots. Then the first plane is expected to arrive in Canada in 2028.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132956">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319805" Type="47">Jeremy Patzer</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896170"> When the U.S. Government Accountability Office stated that the F-35 block 4 upgrade is delayed five years and is at least $6 billion over budget, was that factored into your report, or is that above and beyond as well?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132964">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896171">I believe that the Government Accountability Office issued that notice very recently. My report dates back to the end of 2024 and we released it in June of this year, so no, it would not have factored in information that was not yet available.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132972">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319805" Type="47">Jeremy Patzer</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896172"> Okay.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896173">Even based on incomplete information, is there anything else you flagged as potential cost overruns?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132976">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896174">Our report outlined that we had identified the need for temporary facilities and the need for more training. Those are the minimum right now. Again, many of the plans were not complete, so it's difficult to determine if they will come with additional costs. That's why we issued our recommendations.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896175">This is still very much in the early stages. I would expect that there will be a little more clarity provided over the coming years. More regular monitoring of costs in a proactive way is absolutely needed.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132982">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896176">Thanks.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896177">Ms. Rochefort, go ahead, please.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132987">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319706" Type="47">Pauline Rochefort</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896178"> I will finish my line of questioning with respect to reduction of office space.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896179">You indicated that of the 37 tenants in the first tranche, 15 had not yet signed agreements. I just want to verify who is responsible for signing agreements. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896180">Is there any political involvement in those agreements?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13132995">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896181"> It's my understanding that an office reduction agreement is between the deputy minister of a department and Public Services and Procurement Canada. I can tell you that's the agreement I've signed for my office, so I would imagine that everyone would have to follow a similar process.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133000">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319706" Type="47">Pauline Rochefort</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896182">I have a second question with respect to occupational density targets.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896183">Are there any targets involved in these agreements? If so, from an OECD perspective and from a best practice perspective, are there occupational density targets that are typically set in such agreements?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133010">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896184"> I think this is where every department has to make its own decision about how much occupancy and space it needs. That's why the need to have accurate information about how existing space is being used is so essential to being able to move forward.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896185">Given that we expect auditors to occasionally be out on site auditing entities, I would imagine that my office would have less of a need than a department that would have everyone in every single day because they're policy-driven, and so on.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896186">I think it will really depend, department by department. The public service does so many different activities that I don't think it would be one size fits all.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="20">(1220)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133017">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319706" Type="47">Pauline Rochefort</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896187">Thank you</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133029">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896188">We'll go to Ms. Gaudreau, and then we'll finish with Ms. Jansen and Mr. Sousa. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896189">Go ahead, please.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133038">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="40">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896190">Mr. Chair, since I don't have much time, I will summarize.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896191">We were to study three reports: the report on the acquisition of F‑35 fighter jets, the report on vacant federal office space that needs to be used urgently, and the report on GC Strategies contracts. I will summarize what I have understood, and you can add recommendations in a few seconds.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896192">First, with regard to the subcontracting of GC Strategies contracts, it is not only a matter of accountability and not paying for a service before it is delivered, but security clearances must also be considered. I have heard that it is important to verify the security clearance of subcontractors. When it comes to accountability, it's about providing clarity and evidence so that you can do your job well.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896193">You also mentioned that there are rules. You asked whether, if we forget what has happened in recent years and focus on the present, we could explore, streamline and formulate the rules in the simplest way possible so that all public servants can comply with them.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896194">You also talked about risk assessment. That leads me to say that when we advertise, we need to show what we are looking for through an implementation plan and not be reactive by saying that we did not anticipate certain things. That's basically what I understood, because we could be here for hours.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896195">Are there other aspects we should be vigilant about and pay attention to?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133049">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896196">This is a very broad question. I could give you a list of items, but I'm going to focus on the three reports before us. They show that better cost planning is needed; this issue is often raised in our reports, as is the fact that certain things are missing. So, at the start of a project, it's important to take the time and make the effort to get a good estimate of the costs.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896197">With regard to your comment on good risk management, costs must be closely monitored. When contracts are in a foreign currency, significant currency fluctuations will certainly affect the budget. More rigorous cost monitoring is essential in any project that the government undertakes.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896198">We must also carry out a dynamic analysis of situations. Situations change. When a decision is made, the world continues to turn and change. I think it is also essential to have the flexibility to adjust. This will become apparent during annual monitoring. Vigilance is essential when monitoring a project.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13136119">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896199">Thank you very much.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133061">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="47">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896200">Thank you, Mr. Chair. I appreciate your giving me a bit more time.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133071">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896201"> Thanks very much. I never wish to cut off the AG.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896202">We'll go to Ms. Jansen, please.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133079">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319807" Type="47">Tamara Jansen</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896203">I wanted to go back to affordable housing, if that's all right. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896204">To me, it's clear that it's vulnerable families who are being left out of the affordable housing projects, but according to your report, if I understand it correctly, the only things we're counting are the Liberal promises, as opposed to actual houses being built.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896205">Is that correct?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133086">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896206"> How I would summarize it is that Canada Mortgage and Housing Corporation is going in the right direction. They've got commitments. They're falling short where it matters most, which would be affordability and move-in readiness, but they're going in the right direction. Securing commitments is the right step forward.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="25">(1225)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133094">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319807" Type="47">Tamara Jansen</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896207"> I understood from the report that the federal lands initiative doesn't actually report how many homes are built and ready. It's only reporting things that have been promised or committed to, so Canadians have no clear way of knowing what they're really getting for their tax dollars. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896208">Would you agree? </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133106">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896209"> That's why we noted that their reporting lacked clarity. We felt it needed to include other elements. We gave some examples that could be used. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896210">A commitment is just that. Being move-in ready and understanding when construction has had delays is important. That's why we think that more needs to be added to the public reporting.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133113">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319807" Type="47">Tamara Jansen</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896211"> Is there any transparent way for the public to see how many of these units in these projects are actually being rented out at that so-called affordable rate? Is there a system in place to track that?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133121">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896212"> I believe the Canada Mortgage and Housing Corporation does some reporting. It was, if I'm not mistaken, a little behind. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896213">We did put some information in our report to give you a point-in-time estimate and then made recommendations for CMHC to continue with that accurate reporting. Really, it's up to them to ask what their plans are and when they plan on making that information public.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133127">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319807" Type="47">Tamara Jansen</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896214">So there's no real way for a Canadian to see whether there's something available in an affordable housing unit. There's no way for them to find out where, how many and what's available.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133133">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896215"> I'm not sure I know where to send someone, but I would tell you that what you're looking for will also depend on the definition of affordability. One individual might think something is affordable, while another might not. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896216">I imagine there are municipal resources and provincial resources. I don't think the federal lands initiative will provide all of the information that an individual will need to help find affordable housing in their community.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133138">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319807" Type="47">Tamara Jansen</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896217"> Taxpayers are footing the bill. They deserve to know if these dollars are actually creating those affordable homes or if they are just glossy announcements.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896218">Right now, is there a way for them to go somewhere to see, in their own town or in their own city, which of these units are there and available at the affordable rate?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133144">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896219"> If you're talking about the federal lands initiative, it has public reporting. As I said, that would not be the only place I would look if I were in search of affordable housing.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133150">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319807" Type="47">Tamara Jansen</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896220"> I'm concerned about even the broader risk. Without good transparency in place, isn't there a real risk that the same failures we're seeing in the federal lands initiative are just going to be repeated, only at a much bigger and more expensive scale, in the Build Canada Homes plan?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133156">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896221"> I can't really comment on a project I haven't audited. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896222">Clearly, if the measure of affordability does not have some link to household income, I will raise the same concern that I have raised twice already. I do believe that affordability should be linked to household income, as the national housing strategy calls for and as Statistics Canada uses as a benchmark for affordability in our country.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133162">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319807" Type="47">Tamara Jansen</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896223">I have one more question. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896224">You mentioned that you didn't want to put any more rules in place. What about the idea of a rule saying that you must be able to easily access information as to what affordable housing is available in your own town?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133167">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896225"> You're asking me to comment on a policy decision. I'll leave it up to all of you to decide what the best rules are for the federal public service to follow.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133174">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896226"> That's wonderful.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896227">Mr. Sousa, go ahead, please.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133179">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896228"> Thank you again. I guess we'll wrap up. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896229">There's a line of questioning that reinforces the need for the government to show its response to you in regard to the F-35s and in regard to what we're going to take next. A lot of the questions I'm hearing are for government. I think it's appropriate for us to get that review done so that we can reaffirm your recommendations. I appreciate your putting those forward.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896230">My next item is the professional services contract. You made note that recommendations were made and rules exist and that the government has taken the necessary precautions to ensure that those rules are noted. They just need to be followed. They need to ensure that our public service follows those rules to align with some of the recommendations made by you and others. I'm just recapping that part.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896231">Here's my question now.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896232"> In regard to the modernization of the housing—your third report—you notes that there was resistance from federal tenants in the reallocation of funding. I have a few questions with respect to this. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896233">Could anything have been done to prevent this? What can be done to mitigate this in the future, in regard to the relationship with the tenants?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="30">(1230)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133185">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896234">I'll comment on your comment and then I'll actually get to your question. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896235"> I think it isn't just about following the rules. I do believe that public servants need to understand why the rules are in place. That might help with the application of them. I think that's essential. Adding more rules is what's been happening right now. I would encourage the government to take a step back and streamline in order to speed things up.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896236">Now I have to remember the other question.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133190">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896237"> It had to do with tenants.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133197">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896238">Oh, yes—the tenants. Thank you. I was so excited about procurement rules.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133203">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896239"> Yes, but no, I'm talking now about the delivery of transparency in regard to that.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133205">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896240">Yes, I think this is why we highlighted in the report that not every government department has a financial incentive.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896241"> If you had a financial incentive to reduce your rent, you would most likely try to reduce your footprint if it's underutilized. It is up to the government to figure out the best way to get tenants to agree, whether that's consolidating into buildings or whether that's renovating some of the buildings so that they're more attractive for people to work in. It's whatever incentive they want.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896242"> I would personally encourage my deputy minister colleagues to think about how each of us can support the government's goal of reducing federal office space to help contribute to affordable housing.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133210">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896243">Agreed, and the government has agreed with some of those recommendations.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896244"> I don't know. We can't predict the future. We can't predict future problems. How would you handle those situations that aren't being addressed, such as when they are resisting providing the information?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133216">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896245">I think that Public Services and Procurement Canada needs to enforce compliance. Reducing office space by 50% by 2034 is a stated government objective, and it's up to PSPC to entice and enforce that compliance.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133219">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896246"> This brings us to the last question, to recap this. Let's focus on some of the methodology that exists in some of the other OECD countries.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896247"> My colleague mentioned how Australia calculates the percentage of tenancies meeting the occupational density—the square metres, the long-term employee targets. What is the right target? What do you feel should be established by the Government of Canada?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133224">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896248"> I think that's a difficult question. As I answered before, I don't think it's one size fits all. The space you need in a laboratory will be different from the space you need in an office building.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896249"> I think it is about leveraging the expertise the public service has and understanding how their space is used now, and then looking to best practices in other countries, which is why we highlighted Australia in our report as well. We highlighted the kind of information that they put out there about office space. I believe it would incentivize departments to want to reduce their office space if the federal government had that kind of information in the public domain.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133231">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896250">Of course, the incentive is there to provide greater operational efficiencies. As you say, if it's not one size fits all, the respective average, I think, is what they're using. How are they determining the differences in those spaces?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133237">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896251"> I'm not exactly sure how they're going about it, but I would tell you that the motivation should be that a building, whether it is fully occupied or partially occupied, comes with costs. You need to maintain buildings and you need to operate buildings, and in many of the municipalities, the federal government has to make payments in lieu of taxes, because the government doesn't pay municipal taxes. All of that comes with a cost, and that's why we highlighted the need of.... There are some cost savings. The government estimated the cost at $3.9 billion over 10 years. That could be repurposed.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133242">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896252"> That's a great point, and that's part of what we need to do as we go forward.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896253"> Thank you so much, all of you, for being here today and for your reports.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896254"> That's it, Chair.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133250">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896255"> You took my line, Charles.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896256">
                <B>Voices:</B> Oh, oh!</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896257">
                <B>The Chair:</B> That's why we brought you back today.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896258"> Before all of you pack up and go, I have a couple of quick questions, colleagues, if you don't mind.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896259"> Did you look at the NCC office space at all as part of this study? Have you looked at whether the government is still purchasing office space at the same time that they're trying to reduce their footprint?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133256">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896260"> I can't tell you for sure whether the NCC was in here. We wouldn't have targeted them. We are doing, I believe, a special examination on the National Capital Commission right now, but it won't look specifically at office space.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896261"> Are they acquiring more office space? Over the term of our audit, I don't think that happened.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="35">(1235)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133259">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896262">Are the government and PSPC together still adding office space?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133265">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896263">I actually do not have an answer for that. We didn't look at that. We were focusing in on the plan to reduce it. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133269">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896264"> It's fair to say, though, that they shouldn't be, when the government plan is to go the other way.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133273">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="245353" Type="28">Andrew Hayes</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896265"> The short answer to that question is that it might be more complex. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896266">If certain buildings might not be sustainable, for whatever reasons—maybe the repairs are going to cost more—it might make sense to acquire a different building. Not every building is going to be fit for purpose for a particular organization. I would say that—</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133279">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896267">I would assume, though, that if the government is trying to get rid of 50% of their buildings, they would move over to a government building rather than buy a new building.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133285">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="245353" Type="28">Andrew Hayes</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896268"> For sure, when those buildings will be fit for purpose, but it won't be a one-size-fits-all.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133289">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896269">On the F-35, the review date, the published date, has come and gone. There has been some talk about a dual air force and two different planes. Have you looked at or considered what the added cost would be?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896270">If the government moves away from the F-35, as has been bandied about, and considering how much has been invested there and that the investments in Bagotville and Cold Lake are still going ahead to accommodate the F-35, have you considered it? I'm curious to know if you can give a quick idea about some of the costs that might be involved if that happened.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133294">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896271"> It's difficult to determine the costs should a change in direction happen when we don't even know if a change in direction has happened. I guess what I would offer up is that no—</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133297">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896272">Is the uncertainty about the review affecting things?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133300">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896273">Right now, there's—</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133307">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896274"> Again, the review date has come and gone, but we're still going ahead with investing in some of these buildings.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133311">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896275">I would say that no matter what aircraft the Canadian Armed Forces chooses, they will need trained pilots and they will need upgraded facilities to house them. The technology of the new aircraft is different from the CF-18 technology. No matter what, that training will be needed and that investment will be needed.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896276">
                <B>The Chair:</B> Yes—</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13134379">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896277">I have a point of order, Chair.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13134380">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896278">Go ahead, Mr. Sousa.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133313">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896279"> Just to clarify, there was no review date stated. The review was completed, but there was no—</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13134395">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896280">That's not a point of order, Mr. Sousa, but thank you—</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" id="13133318">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896281">But just to correct the record— </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" id="13134397">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896282"> —for identifying that.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133325">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896283">It was my understanding—</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896284">
                <B>An hon. member:</B> It's in the media today that the report date was missed. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133331">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896285">This is the last question. It relates to the GC Strategies questions. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896286">We had an Order Paper question come back, and there has been an expanded number of files referred to the RCMP. I think it's up to 11 now.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896287">In a previous public accounts meeting I was at, PSPC said they weren't actually forcing repayment of some of these accounts. They were just negotiating with some of the companies that had been found to be improperly charging or defrauding the government.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896288">It may be not the role for you to opine on this, but do you think it tells people that the government is not serious about enforcing their own rules if we're not even forcing repayment—</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133338">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896289"> I think this—</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133344">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896290">—even from companies that we're referring to the RCMP?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133350">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896291">I really can't comment on files that have been referred to the RCMP, but in the case of the elements you're talking about, where PSPC is trying to recover amounts, I believe it's not linked to GC Strategies. It was linked to a bigger, broader—</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133353">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896292">It is—</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133355">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896293">—investigation around a a vendor charging multiple departments for what appeared to be the same seven hours in a day or the same piece of work.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133359">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896294">It's widespread, but the question is, do you think the government should be forcing immediate payment and not doing a negotiation for clearly identified...?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133361">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="262933" Type="28">Karen Hogan</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896295">Once an investigation is done and it's clear that payment was made and services were not rendered, I would expect that overpayments will always be recovered. How the government goes about that is a decision they make, but I would expect that you shouldn't pay for things you didn't receive.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133367">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896296"> Thank you.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896297">Now we'll get to Mr. Sousa's comment on thanking all of you. It's wonderful to see all of you. We're going to suspend very briefly so that everyone can say goodbye.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896298">Mr. Gaheer, please stay on the same Zoom call, because we'll be back in about two minutes.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896299">We are suspended.</ParaText>
              <Pause>
                <StartPause>
                  <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="35">(1235)</Timestamp>
                </StartPause>
                <EndPause>
                  <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="40">(1240)</Timestamp>
                </EndPause>
              </Pause>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13134750">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896300">Thank you for your patience, everyone. We are back.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896301">We have a couple of housekeeping items before we finish for the day.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896302">On the first one, you've seen—</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896303">
                <B>An hon. member:</B> Chair—</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896304">
                <B>The Chair:</B> Oh, yes. I'm sorry. I'll get to you. Can I cover this stuff first? Thanks.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896305">You've seen the budgets for the two meetings. Can I have agreement?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896306">Again, these are not the amounts that we're spending. They are “up to” amounts.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896307">Can I have agreement for the two budgets?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896308">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896309">
                <B>The Chair:</B> That's wonderful. Thank you very much.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896310">Next, you've all received a copy of the recommendations that came out of the subcommittee from last week. This is our path going forward. We are going to keep it flexible, because we're going to work around the schedules for the two ministers, which are always, as we mentioned before, a bit more difficult to work around. Are we all in agreement on the subcommittee report?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896311">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896312">
                <B>The Chair:</B> That's wonderful.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" id="13134755">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896313">Can I clarify something? I'm sorry. I know I'm not on the committee, but—</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133370">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896314">Yes.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133374">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896315">—Ms. Sudds is not here, and she was part of it.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896316">The Canada Lands Company is really not part of PSPC, so I'm not sure if you want housing as a result, because housing is the one it's overseeing. It's item 4. It's not a major issue.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133377">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896317">Canada Lands Company does come to OGGO. We haven't had them in about eight years. It's not definite. It's just one of the ones to consider, but probably not. The priority is the Public Service Integrity Commissioner and the procurement ombudsman. It's not a necessary type of thing, if that makes sense. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="45">(1245)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133381">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896318"> Can I just clarify? I wasn't there. Item 1 was with regard to the consul general's new official residence. Was that discussed? Was that something that was...?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133383">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896319">Yes, it was discussed in the subcommittee. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133386">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896320">It was the subcommittee, I know, and I think Marie was in the subcommittee. I would say that I wasn't there, but was that..? I wasn't sure what.... I've been getting a reference from Ms. Jansen that possibly it wasn't something that she had understood. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133390">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896321">No, it was to move forward to the report, and she was there. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896322">Marie-Hélène, did you wish...?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133394">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="40">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896323">What I understand, Mr. Chair, is that we have to get started. We began this morning and are in the process of setting the agenda. Obviously, this will depend as usual on availability. We have given ourselves some leeway to ensure we have a good agenda. At the same time, there are some dates that we can already confirm. I am thinking in particular of the two meetings. We are talking about a report. We decided that we should at least finish all the reports related to the previous Parliament without reopening them.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896324">It is absolutely certain that we need to establish what we will do over the next few weeks. We are recommending this for good reason.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133398">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896325">Yes, that is correct. Thanks very much. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896326">We'll move forward.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896327">Let's see, what else do we have? It's to adopt a budget. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896328">From time to time, colleagues—</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896329">I'm sorry, Madame. Please go ahead. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133402">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="40">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896330">Time is flying by, but I would like to move a notice of motion. I don't want it debated today. I have it in both official languages. I will read it to you, and then I will send it to you right after I read it. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133406">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896331">May I interrupt? </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896332">I'm going to go through my stuff first. Then Ms. Block had her hand up for a motion, and then we'll get to yours. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896333">From time to time, we get ATIP requests for committee business. We had a request from DND. I'm going to bore everybody and read out something. This is the first time this has come up in about a year.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896334">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">On August 25, 2025, the Department of National Defence identified our committee as a third party with regard to records that are now subject to a request made under the Act. </QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896335">This was sent October 15. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896336">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">Committees receive such requests from time to time, and OGGO is no exception. Usually, they are straightforward, and we have a well-established process for them. Since this is the first time most of you are encountering such a procedure, please let me give you more detailed explanations for context. </QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896337">I'm just going to read it verbatim from our clerk.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896338">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">The Access to Information Act gives the public the right to access records held by various government institutions, subject to certain exceptions. Even if the House of Commons, including its standing committees, is constitutionally and legally independent from the federal government and is not subject to the Act, it may receive third party notices from government institutions when the requested materials contain information relating to the business of the House or a committee.</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896339">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">On December 2, 2013, the House of Commons adopted the Forty-Second Report of the Standing Committee on Procedure and House Affairs (PROC) regarding parliamentary privilege and access to information. The report established the process to be followed by committees when they receive third party notices under the Act.</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896340">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">The records at issue here consist of email exchanges between the clerk of OGGO to the Department inviting the Minister and other officials to appear during the ArriveCAN application....</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896341">It wasn't on any other information. It was solely the clerk sending out an email inviting someone. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896342">It is up to us whether we wish to release it. I'm going to suggest we do so, because there is nothing there except the clerk inviting the minister to attend, but we do need the committee's approval to release that information.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133410">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319808" Type="47">Kelly Block</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896343">Do you need a motion to that effect? </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133415">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896344">No. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896345">We're all fine? That's perfect. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133419">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="40">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896346">Mr. Chair, I have a lot of respect for our interpreters. I think the committee has been sitting for two hours. Even my brain is starting to get tired.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896347">I just want to make sure of one thing. When we talk about access to information…. I need to hear it again, because I want to be sure I understand correctly. I was on the Standing Committee on Procedure and House Affairs. We received an email asking for a witness to come…. Please explain that to me again.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="50">(1250)</Timestamp>
          <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133423">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896348"> It was an ATIP request that came to National Defence. Part of what it covers is with regard to ArriveCAN. They are requesting information under the Access to Information Act. We are just asking if it's okay to release the information that pertains to OGGO. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896349">In this case, it's solely the email inviting people to the committee. If it was something more sensitive, chances are that we would say no, but in this case, it's solely the email invitation. Rather than saying no and raising flags, I suggest that we just release the email. Are we agreed?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896350">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896351">
                <B>The Chair:</B> That's perfect. I will remember to speak more slowly for the interpretation.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896352">This is the last item, I believe. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896353">Mr. Gill is what we consider an associate member. I'm just seeking the committee's approval to include him on the email distribution list, give him access to our digital binder going forward and allow him to attend in camera sessions.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896354">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896355">
                <B>The Chair:</B> I had Mrs. Block, and then I'll go to you, Madame Gaudreau—</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133427">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319708" Type="47">Vince Gasparro</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896356">Mr. Chair, I just want to make sure that any of our associate members will also be extended a similar courtesy, if that's okay.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133431">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896357"> If you're bringing someone on, it's kind of unusual. If they're a regular permanent associate member.... For the sake of argument, if Mr. Sousa is going to be with us each and every time but is not an official member and needs to be subbed in, then yes, but it's not for every parliamentarian, if that makes sense.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13134194">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319708" Type="47">Vince Gasparro</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896358">Yes, that makes sense.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13134198">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896359">It's not that we wouldn't dearly love to have Mr. Sousa back. It's wonderful to have you back, Mr. Sousa. I tease you.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896360">We'll go to Mrs. Block and then Ms. Gaudreau.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133435">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319808" Type="47">Kelly Block</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896361"> Thank you very much, Mr. Chair.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896362">I'm actually going to retract my request.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13134208">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896363">Okay, then we'll go to Ms. Gaudreau.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133440">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="40">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896364">Essentially, our interpreters' contract is expiring. Therefore, I think it would be important to make this a notice of motion. As you will see, it is not prescriptive.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896365">I will read the motion slowly and send it to you in both official languages.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896366">The motion is as follows:</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896367">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="2" IndentRest="2">That pursuant to Standing Order 108(3)(c), the committee hold a two-hour meeting in the very near future to review the renewal of the contract for parliamentary interpreters and ensure that the quality and professional standard of interpretation services are maintained, in full compliance with the right of parliamentarians to express themselves and work in either official language; that the committee invite, as soon as possible, the Minister of Government Transformation, Public Works and Procurement, as well as Canadian representatives of the International Association of Conference Interpreters.</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896368">I'll send you the text of the motion, Mr. Chair.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133444">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896369"> Are you intending to table this motion right now, or is it for the future?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896370">It's for the future. Okay.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133448">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="40">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896371">I want to move the notice of motion, but since we will have a busy schedule over the next few weeks, we simply need to set a date. In my opinion, this will be by the end of 2025.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="55">(1255)</Timestamp>
          <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133452">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896372"> I'm sorry. Do you wish to move it right now, or are you just reading it into the record? </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896373"> Are you just giving notice? </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13134161">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="40">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896374">This is a notice of motion; I do not want to debate it now.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896375">Please remind me of the procedure, Mr. Chair. If I move this motion, we will get to debate it later, correct?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133468">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896376">You can read it into the record to put it on notice for a later discussion.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133473">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321021" Type="40">Marie-Hélène Gaudreau</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896377">I want us to discuss this later. I am mindful of the time.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <FloorLanguage language="EN">[<I>English</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13133476">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896378"> Okay. That's wonderful.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896379">I understand it's two hours. If we can finalize it when we have the <Affiliation DbId="318684" Type="4">PSPC minister</Affiliation>, we'll see, rather than have them appear twice in a short period. Perhaps they can extend it a tiny bit and we can wrap it up at the same time, but we'll follow up when we confirm the minister's attendance.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8896380">If there's nothing else, I will thank Charles for being with us again.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13134142">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="317799" Type="2">Charles Sousa</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896381"> It was my pleasure.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13134147">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="321013" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8896382">We are adjourned.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
    </OrderOfBusiness>
  </HansardBody>
</Hansard>