<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Hansard xml:lang="EN" id="13141245">
  <StartPageNumber>1</StartPageNumber>
  <DocumentTitle>
    <DocumentName>EVIDENCE</DocumentName>
  </DocumentTitle>
  <ExtractedInformation>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InstitutionDebate">Standing Committee on Official Languages</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Number">NUMBER 002</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Session">1st SESSION</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Parliament">45th PARLIAMENT</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Date">Thursday, September 25, 2025</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="DateOtherLang">Le jeudi 25 septembre 2025</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Institution">Standing Committee on Official Languages</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Country">CANADA</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="RecordingNote">[Recorded by Electronic Apparatus]</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="HeaderTitle">EVIDENCE</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="HeaderDate">September 25, 2025</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDocumentCategory">Committee</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaTitle">NUMBER 002</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaTitleEn">NUMBER 002</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaTitleFr">NUMÉRO 002</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaNumberNumber">02</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDateNumDay">25</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDateNumMonth">09</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaDateNumYear">2025</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaCreationTime">2025/09/25 11:00:00</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="MetaInstitution">House Of Commons</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InstitutionDebateFr">Comité permanent des langues officielles</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InstitutionDebateEn">Standing Committee on Official Languages</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="Acronyme">LANG</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="SpeakerTitle">Chair</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="SpeakerName">Yvan Baker</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="SessionNumber">1</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="ParliamentNumber">45</ExtractedItem>
    <ExtractedItem Name="InCameraNote" />
  </ExtractedInformation>
  <HansardBody>
    <OrderOfBusiness>
      <CatchLine />
      <SubjectOfBusiness>
        <SubjectOfBusinessContent>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="00">(1100)</Timestamp>
          <FloorLanguage language="FR">[<I>Translation</I>]</FloorLanguage>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141248">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair (Yvan Baker (Etobicoke Centre, Lib.))</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902551">I call the meeting to order. Welcome to meeting number two of the House of Commons Standing Committee on Official Languages.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902552">Before we begin, I'd like to tell you how fortunate I feel to be sitting with you all, from all the parties, on the Standing Committee on Official Languages. Ever since I was young, I remember my parents telling me that our official languages are at the heart of our identity as a country and as Canadians. I therefore look forward to working with you on this issue, which is so important to Canadians.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902553">I need to read a few things before we move to our agenda and start our work.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902554">I'd like to ask all in-person participants to consult the guidelines written on the updated cards on the table. These measures are in place to help prevent audio and feedback incidents, and to protect the health and safety of all participants, including the interpreters. You'll also notice a QR code on the card which links to a short awareness video.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902555">Today's meeting is taking place in a hybrid format. For those participating remotely, please click on the microphone icon to activate the microphone and please put yourself on mute when you're not speaking.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902556">I'd like to remind participants of the following points. Please wait until I recognize you before speaking. All comments must be addressed through the chair. I'd ask you to raise your hand if you wish to speak, whether you are attending in person or on Zoom. The committee clerk and I will do our best to maintain the speaking order. It is essential to ensure that only one person speaks at a time, not only to maintain order but also to assist the interpreters.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902557">In terms of our agenda, we will start with committee business. The subcommittee's report was distributed to committee members yesterday, and we are meeting today to discuss it. I'd like to move that we begin with our discussion on this report. If there are any other matters that members wish to raise relating to committee business, we could discuss them after. Do you all agree?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902558">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> Yes.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13146935">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902559">Agreed. The subcommittee report has been distributed. Is it the pleasure of the committee to adopt the report or would any members like to speak?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902560">Mr. Godin, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141258">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin (Portneuf—Jacques-Cartier, CPC)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902561">Mr. Chair, for the benefit of all the new committee members, I'd like to give a reminder.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902562">As per our usual practice, the sub-committee is responsible for planning our fall agenda, and that is what my colleague Guillaume Deschênes‑Thériault, Mario Beaulieu from the Bloc Québécois, you, Mr. Chair, the analyst, the clerk and I did on Thursday.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902563">This plan outlines everything we discussed during our meeting on Tuesday. I therefore move its adoption so we can begin our meetings next week and move our cause forward.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902564">Thank you, Mr. Chair.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141260">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902565">Thank you, Mr. Godin.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902566">Mr. Beaulieu, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141262">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu (La Pointe-de-l'Île, BQ)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902567">Mr. Chair, I have two amendments to move.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902568">The first has to do with prioritization. We know that French is under threat in Quebec more than ever, as it is across Canada. All language indicators show that French is in decline. Even Statistics Canada's predictive study indicates that in Quebec, the percentage of French as the language used at home will decrease from 81.6% in 2011 to 73.6% by 2036. It was 83.1% in 2001. In the last census—the 2021 census—it was 79.1%. What's more, those forecasts were made in a context of lower immigration than observed in recent years, and they are probably overly optimistic. Over the past few years, several Liberal ministers recognized from the outset that the use of French is in decline, that French is under threat from all sides and that there are 8 million francophones surrounded by 360 million anglophones in Canada and North America.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902569">These factors were partially reflected in the new Official Languages Act, even though there was a setback. Rather than promoting only French in Quebec, we've reverted to the old notion of parallelism in order to defend anglophones in Quebec as a minority.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902570">Finally, we looked at the Action Plan for Official Languages 2023-2028: Protection-Promotion-Collaboration, and there is nothing new for French. Everything is about promoting English within Quebec. I looked at the Canada Public Accounts for 2024 and it's the same thing: I didn't see anything for French in Quebec, or practically nothing—$100 million a year. If we go back a bit to what has been done since the Official Languages Act began, we are now at over $3.6 billion that has contributed to anglicizing Quebec. In constant dollars, it's over $5.5 billion.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902571">So I think that the study on measures to promote French—we want to see what's coming—should be prioritized and done first. I so move and I would like to know if my colleagues agree.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902572">I also have a second amendment to move, but I don't know if you want me to move it right away, Mr. Chair.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="05">(1105)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141274">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902573">Mr. Beaulieu, I've consulted with the clerk, and we'll proceed with one proposal at a time.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902574">Just so it's clear for everyone, can you tell us what exactly it is that you're proposing?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141277">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902575">This motion calls for a study of measures that have been and will be taken to protect and promote French in Quebec. That is in the Official Languages Act, but nothing has been done. Moreover, this study is the last item in the motion, which suggests that, for the Liberals and the Conservatives, French in Quebec is a low-priority item. I believe it should be a high priority, and that's what we should start with.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141278">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902576">Okay.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902577">If I understand correctly, you're proposing that we begin with this study.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141279">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902578">Yes.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141281">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902579">Okay.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902580">Mr. Godin, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141282">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902581">Mr. Chair, with all due respect for my colleague, I would like to say that I, too, acknowledge the decline of French, and not just in Quebec. I'm saying that because this is a federal Parliament. There are 10 provinces and three territories. Every one of them has francophone communities. I think that's important. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902582">It's also important to remember that we wrapped up the 44th Parliament with a study on the education continuum. Our vision must be comprehensive and national in scope, and I'm not going to disrespect all those organizations across Canada, including in Quebec, by tossing that study aside. I think it's important to complete that study first. We have maybe four to six meetings left if I remember correctly, and I think it's important. We've done work on this. My colleague wants us to throw all that work in the trash and focus only on Quebec and the decline of French in Quebec. French is in decline across Canada. I think it's important to finish our study on the education continuum.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902583">There's a habit in this kind of situation, unfortunately, and it's reasonable to understand the intentions of those responsible for bilingualism and the Official Languages Act. Two ministers have been invited, the <Affiliation DbId="318664" Type="4">Minister responsible for Official Languages</Affiliation> and the <Affiliation DbId="318605" Type="4">President of the Treasury Board</Affiliation>, and I think it's important to hear what they have to say.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902584">We've shown we are open to Mr. Beaulieu's proposed study by agreeing to it, but we disagree on how to prioritize things. I disagree with his proposal.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="10">(1110)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141295">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902585">Okay, thank you Mr. Godin.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902586">Mr. Deschênes‑Thériault, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141298">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319660" Type="47">Guillaume Deschênes-Thériault (Madawaska—Restigouche, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902587">Thank you, Mr. Chair.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902588">I completely agree that measures to protect and promote French across Canada are important. We acknowledge the decline of French, and we need to address this issue. I believe that's why the subcommittee agreed to our Bloc colleague's study proposal, which we amended to give it a Canada-wide scope. I think we need to look at the protection and promotion of French in every province and territory. This is an important matter, so we added the proposed study to our list of priorities.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902589">However, we agreed to finish the study on the education continuum, which is also of critical importance because education is how people acquire the language of a culture. That's why education is so important in a minority francophone context. We undertook substantive work on that in the 44th Parliament. I believe the community stakeholders who appeared before us and those who have yet to appear are eagerly awaiting our committee's findings.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902590">I feel that the order we proposed in no way detracts from my colleague's study, nor does it reflect how important we think it is. We recognize the importance of measures to protect and promote French. However, I suggest we keep the proposed order of business. We'll start with our education study. There's also a study on the digital transformation and the impact of AI on official languages, especially French, which is also a very timely and important topic. Those are three important topics. I would like us to maintain the proposed order of business.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141304">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902591">Thank you, Mr. Deschênes‑Thériault.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902592">Mr. Beaulieu, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141306">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902593">The issue of francophones outside of Quebec is very important to the Bloc Québécois. That's why I agreed to move this motion yet again. One would think people here are allergic to Quebec. They never want to focus on Quebec.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141307">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902594">I have a point of order, Mr. Chair.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902595">I don't think my colleague should be imputing motives. This is a federal Parliament, and we govern all of Canada. I would like him to withdraw his remarks.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141311">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902596">I don't see how I imputed motives at all. I stated facts.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902597">I presented the first study that was done on the promotion of French a few years ago, which took a very long time. As part of our study, we included francophones outside Quebec. We included anglophones. Then prorogation happened. It took two or three elections to get through the clause-by-clause study of the new Official Languages Act.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902598">Assuming everyone around the table is acting in good faith, I am prepared to make a concession if necessary. I'm open to the idea of continuing the study on the education continuum and then studying the promotion of French in Quebec.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902599">Clearly, if French continues to decline at this rate in Quebec, that will be detrimental to all francophones outside Quebec, be they Acadians or Franco-Ontarians, because the root cause is the same. However, 90% of francophones live in Quebec. Since the Official Languages Act came into force, the Canadian government has focused solely on promoting English in Quebec. It is as if they are trying to weaken French where it is strongest. I think this has gone on long enough. We need to move on.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902600">I therefore propose that we study the Quebec issue after completing the education continuum study.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141322">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902601">We're still discussing the point of order.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902602">Mr. Godin, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141323">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902603">I was done with my point of order.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902604">Regarding Mr. Beaulieu's remarks, I see that he's not withdrawing them. I respect that; it's perfectly fine.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902605">That said, we're putting the cart before the horse. We have to be realistic. What we have on the agenda for this fall is finishing the education continuum study, meeting with the <Affiliation DbId="318605" Type="4">President of the Treasury Board</Affiliation>, meeting with the <Affiliation DbId="318664" Type="4">Minister responsible for Official Languages</Affiliation> and the AI study.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902606">Let's also keep in mind that we will have to rearrange our schedule to prioritize the Official Languages Act regulations once they're tabled this fall. I think and I hope that the regulations will include tools to combat the decline of French across Canada, including in Quebec. I'm sure they will. It's been three years, and I'm sure the people drafting them have sharpened their pencils and will come up with a great set of regulations. Fingers crossed.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902607">I therefore suggest that we wait and see what's in the regulations. I stand by my position. I'm very comfortable with what was discussed and what was proposed by the subcommittee today.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="15">(1115)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141337">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902608">Thank you. Give me a moment to consult the clerk.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902609">Mr. Dalton, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141340">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319797" Type="47">Marc Dalton (Pitt Meadows—Maple Ridge, CPC)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902610">I'm pleased to be a member of this committee again. Regarding Mr. Beaulieu's motion, my take as a member from British Columbia is that we need to look at what's going on across Canada because the decline is being observed everywhere.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902611">Last year, we did several studies at the same time, and it was a little confusing. This time, I think we should proceed more systematically. We should finish the education continuum study, then move on to other studies.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141344">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902612">Thank you.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902613">Ms. Chenette, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141348">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319661" Type="47">Madeleine Chenette (Thérèse-De Blainville, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902614">Thank you, Mr. Chair.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902615">I'm very happy to be part of this committee, which is so important for our official languages. I'm a proud Quebecker, and I think that, if we want to work well as a committee, we have to keep in mind that, as Quebeckers, we also represent our federation. I'm concerned about both languages in Quebec, especially French, but, as my colleagues have said, it's important that we address concerns that affect Canada's francophonie as a whole. I therefore fully support what my Conservative colleagues said.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902616">I know my colleagues agree about the education continuum study, but I'd like to talk about the proposed study on the repercussions of the digital transformation on official languages. I would like to congratulate the people who did such excellent background work on this for the committee and who came up with this proposal. That's important work, and it makes our lives easier.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902617">I understand the importance of discussing those repercussions. A major digital transformation is under way, and we can't wait until it's too late to discuss the impact on official languages. It's important to be proactive about having those discussions and to think about those impacts. This may also help us have a more informed discussion afterward.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902618">That's why I was partial to the order the proposed studies were in. We'll look at draft regulations and the digital transformation our society is going through, which will impact our official languages. We'll see whether those impacts are positive or not, then we can have a conversation once we've gathered all the necessary data. If we follow the order the subcommittee came up with, we won't have to rehash things when we talk about the digital transformation.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141360">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902619">Mr. Beaulieu, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141362">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902620">I'd like to point out that the Bloc Québécois has been raising this issue for years. All the federal government has done so far is strengthen English and anglicize Quebec. The Official Languages Act anglicizes Quebec because its official language support programs subsidize English almost exclusively. French is declining. The more time we waste like this, the more it will decline and less will be done to address that.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902621">I agree that we should finish the education continuum study, but then we'll have the AI study and everything else. Ministers will send us their availability, and their appearances might happen right in the middle of our studies.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902622">In short, my position remains the same, and I'd like us to vote if nobody else has anything to add.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141369">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902623">If there are no further comments, let's vote.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902624">(Amendment negatived: nays 8; yeas 1)</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141370">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902625">Mr. Beaulieu, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="20">(1120)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141375">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902626">Thank you.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902627">We agree with recommendation (b), pertaining to interpreters. However, we know a new contract is going to be signed. Interpreters and the International Association of Conference Interpreters are concerned about this new measure because it will probably have fewer requirements. Interpretation quality, which often leaves something to be desired as it is, will further decline, so we must address this urgently.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902628">Once we've voted on the main motion, it will be very difficult to amend this specific recommendation, so I suggest we modify it now by replacing “as soon as possible” with “no later than Tuesday, October 7”. We can send that amendment in writing if you want.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141386">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902629">The clerk would like your amendment in writing.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902630">Is that all, Mr. Beaulieu?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141388">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902631">Yes.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141390">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902632">Would anyone like to speak to Mr. Beaulieu's proposal?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141392">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902633">I'd like the analyst to help me find the recommendation, which I don't see in the report.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141393">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902634">We emailed it.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141395">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902635">Okay. Sorry, I was confused. As I said earlier, these are our first meetings, and I have to get back into the swing of things.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902636">I agree with my colleague, and I'm glad I put forward this recommendation to study the interpreter situation and emphasize how important it is for parliamentarians to have access to their services. As long as we have a Canadian Parliament and a bilingual, French and English country, I think all parliamentarians should have access to interpretation services.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902637">In recent years, we've seen these services decline in quantity, though not in quality. Also, we learned this summer that the government launched a bidding process that, as my Bloc Québécois colleague said, could tie our hands as of January 2026, based on my understanding. I think it's important to deal with this.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902638">I'm the one who put forward this recommendation, so I agree with my colleague, but we need some flexibility to replace the October 7 date with a later date. We may have to check with the clerk to see when the ministers are available before we lock that date in.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141403">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902639">Thank you, Mr. Godin.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902640">Ms. Chenette, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141404">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319661" Type="47">Madeleine Chenette</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902641">Once again, we're in favour of having that discussion about interpreters, which is a very important issue to all of us.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902642">I share my colleague's concern about the October 7 date. Obviously this has to happen in October, but we need some flexibility around scheduling the meeting. We can see when the witnesses are available because a lot of things are happening at once.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902643">We're ready to talk about it.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141411">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902644">Mr. Godin, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141413">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902645">My colleague has invited me to consult the calendar. We must remember that today is September 25. The committee will not meet on September 30, but will meet on October 2 and 7. We must also check the dates on which <Affiliation DbId="318664" Type="4">Minister Guilbeault</Affiliation> and <Affiliation DbId="318605" Type="4">Minister Ali</Affiliation> are required to appear, but that will be before October 7. Mathematically, what my colleague from the Bloc is proposing is therefore impossible. That is why I suggest extending the deadline to Thursday, October 23, but without limiting myself to that date.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="25">(1125)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141418">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902646">We could agree on a date between October 7 and October 23.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141419">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902647">Yes, absolutely. I am open to that.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141420">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902648">There is a good chance that the ministers will refuse the proposed dates or delay their appearance, as we have seen in the past. So, we could say that the goal is to hold the meeting before October 7. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141422">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902649">Excuse me, Mr. Chair, I misled the committee: The ministers must appear before November 7, not before October 7.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141425">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902650">So, if we want more flexibility, we can set the deadline for October 16, or indicate that this is a target date. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141432">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902651">There is no parliamentary business during the week of October 13. How about October 21?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141437">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902652">Agreed. So the meeting must be held no later than Tuesday, October 21.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141441">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902653">Before we continue, I want to clarify what you are proposing. You are proposing that the meeting regarding interpreters be held no later than October 21.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902654">Mr. Deschênes‑Thériault, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141443">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319660" Type="47">Guillaume Deschênes-Thériault</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902655">I believe this is in line with what was proposed to the subcommittee. There was talk of holding this meeting in early October, between two meetings of the study on the education continuum. That way, we would have time to invite additional witnesses to this study, if we wished to do so.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902656">I therefore support my colleague Mr. Beaulieu’s proposal to hold the meeting on interpreters by October 21.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141446">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902657">Mr. Beaulieu, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141447">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902658">It would be preferable to hold the meeting before October 21, because there is a risk that October 21 will be too late. If the government adopts its new rules before October 21, we are told that it will be too late. The die will be cast.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141448">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902659">Agreed.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902660">I would ask the clerk to read the text as amended by the proposed amendment.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141451">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="318903" Type="27">The Clerk of the Committee (Madeleine Martin)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902661">Following the amendment moved by Mr. Beaulieu, the first part of paragraph 1(b) of the subcommittee’s report would read as follows: </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902662">
                <Quote>
                  <QuotePara Align="Left" IndentFirst="3" IndentRest="2">That, pursuant to Standing Order 108(3)(f), the Standing Committee on Official Languages hold a two-hour meeting to examine the situation surrounding the renewal of the interpreters’ contract, as long as the meeting is held no later than Tuesday, October 21;</QuotePara>
                  <QuotePara IndentFirst="3" IndentRest="2">…</QuotePara>
                </Quote>
              </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141452">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902663">Is the committee in favour of this amendment?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902664">Mr. Godin, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141453">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902665">I have a question about procedure, Mr. Chair. I believe that a member cannot propose a subamendment to modify his own amendment.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902666">What do you think, Madam Clerk?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141455">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902667">You are correct, Mr. Godin. This is one of my first meetings as chair. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141458">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902668">I wasn’t criticizing you, Mr. Chair.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902669">I will therefore propose the subamendment that amends Mr. Beaulieu’s amendment.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141461">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902670">Thank you very much.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902671">Does the committee wish to adopt the proposed change?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902672">(The amendment as amended agreed to)</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13147066">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902673">Are there any other comments on the subcommittee’s report?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902674">Mr. Beaulieu, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141463">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902675">Since our meeting is public and people in Quebec are following our work, I would like to point out that the study on new measures to protect and promote the French language has been postponed several times. Once again, it has been put at the bottom of the list.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141466">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902676">Ms. Chenette, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141467">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319661" Type="47">Madeleine Chenette</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902677">I would like to say that we are all aware, around this table, that French has an important place in Quebec and throughout Canada. We also need to establish our priorities in order to foster an even richer discussion on the subject, which we must debate this year, as we all agree.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="30">(1130)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141470">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902678">There do not seem to be any other comments.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902679">Is it the committee’s wish to adopt the subcommittee’s report? </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141473">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902680">I am abstaining because of the priority of studies.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141474">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902681">Very well.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902682">Mr. Godin, you have the floor. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141475">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902683">I withdraw my speaking request.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141477">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902684">Very well.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902685">We have two options: Either we adopt the report on division, or we proceed to a recorded division.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141479">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902686">I request a recorded division.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141483">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902687">Very well.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902688">Madam Clerk, can you please proceed to the recorded division on the subcommittee’s report?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902689">(Motion agreed to: yeas 8; nays 0. [<I>See Minutes of Proceedings</I>])</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902690">Are there any other topics the members would like to discuss?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902691">Mr. Godin, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141490">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902692">Mr. Chair, this is not something I do, and I don’t want to surprise anyone. </ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902693">I had a chance to look at this quickly with my colleagues, and I request unanimous consent to introduce a motion.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141494">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902694">Mr. Godin, since we are discussing the business of the committee, you do not need unanimous consent to present the motion. However, if you decide to present it, I ask that you send it in writing to the clerk, and that you read it.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141503">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902695">Mr. Chair, I want to reassure my colleagues. It is not my habit to proceed in this manner. We are at the beginning of our work and there have been some staff changes. You will notice that the chair behind me is empty, and I invite anyone interested in working on the Standing Committee on Official Languages files to contact my office to help Mr. Godin do his job. This is a part-time position. There you have it, I’ve advertised and posted my job offer.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902696">Let’s get right to the heart of the matter. Last week, an article mentioned that Cogeco Media wanted to broadcast less French-language music. That is a reality. Coming from a television and radio broadcasting background, I am aware that this is a problem for companies from an economic standpoint. However, given the decline of French in Quebec and across Canada, I am not prepared to see a decrease in the proportion of French-language music.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902697"> I therefore invite the committee to consider the following motion. I move that, pursuant to Standing Order 108(3)(f), the Standing Committee on Official Languages hold a two-hour meeting as soon as possible to examine the situation regarding the recent request by Cogeco to reduce quotas for French music content as required by the conditions in their broadcasting licence. That, as part of this meeting, the committee hear from: broadcasters such as Cogeco, Bell, RNC or Leclerc Communication, as well as from a representative from ADISQ, the Association québécoise de l’industrie du disque, du spectacle et de la vidéo. That the purpose of this meeting be to understand the current situation and to evaluate other possible solutions in order to respect the objective of stopping the decline of French.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902698">I think it is important to consider this issue. It is a problem that has been going on for several years, and it is in the interest of everyone here on the committee to promote measures to halt the decline of French. That is the committee’s objective.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902699">Here, we are dealing with a very specific current issue. Cogeco is before the Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission, an emergency situation similar to the one my colleague was talking about. This study is not very time-consuming, and I think it can be included in the committee’s schedule. This could make it easier for the clerk to plan our work. I think that’s important.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902700">We are not here to attack broadcasters. We are here to work with them to find solutions that are profitable and viable for them, without their attacking the French language and francophone music.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="35">(1135)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141522">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902701">Thank you, Mr. Godin. We will now suspend the meeting.</ParaText>
              <Pause>
                <StartPause>
                  <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="35">(1135)</Timestamp>
                </StartPause>
                <EndPause>
                  <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="50">(1150)</Timestamp>
                </EndPause>
              </Pause>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141691">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902702">We are resuming the meeting.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902703">Before continuing the discussion on this topic, I would like to mention that at 12:30 p.m., the Franco-Ontarian flag will be raised in front of the Parliament Building. I know that many of the members here would like to attend. Ultimately, it is up to the committee to decide, but I wanted us to be aware of this so that we could see if it would be possible to resolve the issues we still have to discuss today. It would be great to be able to attend the flag-raising ceremony.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902704"> Mr. Villeneuve has the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141695">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319658" Type="47">Louis Villeneuve (Brome—Missisquoi, Lib.)</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902705">Thank you.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902706">This is my first time participating in committee work, and I see that there are people here who have a lot of experience.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902707">I wanted to start by saying that I am a strong advocate for our two official languages throughout Canada. I am a francophone from the Limoilou neighbourhood in Quebec City. We are not that far away.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902708">Earlier, Mr. Godin said that it was rare for him to propose a motion at the last minute. I must say that I am in favour of what he proposed. I think it is very important to have a significant percentage of French-language songs in our media. That said, I will now give the floor to Mr. Deschênes‑Thériault, as we have a few minor amendments to make.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141698">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902709">Mr. Deschênes‑Thériault has the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141699">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319660" Type="47">Guillaume Deschênes-Thériault</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902710">Thank you, Mr. Chair.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902711">We agree with the motion and would simply like to add online broadcasters such as Netflix or Amazon Prime, among others, to the list of suggested witnesses, as well as a representative from the Alliance des radios communautaires du Canada. I believe an email has been sent to the clerk with this proposed amendment. We believe this is an opportunity to broaden the discussion on the nature of online broadcasters’ obligations to provide French-language content. This is also a timely topic. Inviting the Alliance des radios communautaires du Canada could broaden the discussion to include the entire country, since this organization represents community radio stations from coast to coast.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141714">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902712">Mr. Dalton has the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141716">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319797" Type="47">Marc Dalton</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902713">I don’t understand how the amendment can control the percentage of French-language music online. People can choose what they listen to. It’s a bit confusing.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141721">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902714">Mr. Beaulieu has the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141725">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902715">The fact that a French-language broadcaster in Quebec is asking to reduce the quota for French-language music demonstrates the urgency of the situation.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902716">I am in favour of the proposal, but I did not quite understand: Would this involve inviting representatives from Netflix, among others? </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="11" Mn="55">(1155)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141731">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319660" Type="47">Guillaume Deschênes-Thériault</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902717">You’re right, there is a little confusion.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902718">We propose inviting online broadcasters to talk about their French-language content. It’s not necessarily a question of quotas for French-language songs, but rather of obligations to produce and broadcast French-language content. That’s the idea behind the amendment. If the committee agrees, I would simply propose inviting online broadcasters to talk specifically about their French-language content, not necessarily French-language songs.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141738">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902719">In that case, I would propose a subamendment to indicate that the committee will hold “at least one meeting” on the issue. Indeed, if we invite several guests, at least one meeting would be necessary. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141743">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902720">Before continuing, since Mr. Godin reminded me earlier that there are rules to follow, I would like to ask Mr. Deschênes‑Thériault to clarify his amendment.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141744">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319660" Type="47">Guillaume Deschênes-Thériault</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902721">Basically, the proposed amendment mentioned online broadcasters such as Netflix and Amazon Prime, among others, and we also proposed inviting a representative from the Alliance des radios communautaires du Canada. I propose clarifying that we would invite online broadcasters such as Netflix and Amazon Prime, among others, to talk to us about “their French-language content.”</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902722">I’m thinking out loud, but I think Mr. Godin has a suggestion I’d like to hear.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141752">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902723">I would just like to clarify that we are now discussing the amendment only.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141753">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319660" Type="47">Guillaume Deschênes-Thériault</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902724">I think Mr. Godin wants to propose a better wording for my amendment.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13146411">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902725">Very well.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141755">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902726">Mr. Chair, I do think it is unnecessary to consult broadcasters who are not necessarily concerned. I think that by replacing the reference to Netflix and others with “online broadcasters of French-language content,” we would eliminate those who are not involved in this issue.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902727">This is a relevant request, because the objective of this mini-study is to find possible solutions and work with people and artisans to see how we can further promote the French language. I am comfortable with that.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902728">I therefore move my subamendment, which would allow for broader application.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141763">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902729">Since we must follow procedure and the rules, I would like to ask the clerk if everything is clear to her regarding the initial amendment proposed by Mr. Deschênes‑Thériault. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141765">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="318903" Type="27">The Clerk</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902730">Mr. Deschênes‑Thériault, I would like to clarify something.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902731">If I understand correctly, your initial amendment proposed inviting online broadcasters such as Netflix and Amazon Prime, among others. Mr. Godin’s subamendment consists of removing this reference to Netflix and Amazon Prime and instead inviting “online broadcasters of French-language content.”</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902732">Could you repeat the second part of your initial amendment?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141769">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319660" Type="47">Guillaume Deschênes-Thériault</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902733">I suggested we invite a representative of the Alliance des radios communautaires du Canada.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141770">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902734">Right now, we are only discussing Mr. Godin’s subamendment.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902735">Mr. Godin, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141775">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902736">In fact, Mr. Chair, my colleague from the Bloc Québécois has a very pertinent comment: “a representative of the Alliance des radios communautaires du Canada that broadcasts French-language content.”</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141779">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319660" Type="47">Guillaume Deschênes-Thériault</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902737">We do not need to add this clarification, as the alliance’s members are francophones in a minority situation. It is a francophone organization. The Alliance des radios communautaires du Canada has been managing community radio stations in French-speaking communities in Canada since the 1990s.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902738">However, with regard to the subamendment proposed by Mr. Godin, I would suggest that we proceed by….</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="00">(1200)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141781">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319661" Type="47">Madeleine Chenette</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902739">That’s because—</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141784">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902740">Ms. Chenette, I will give you the floor in a minute, but, once again, we must follow the proper process.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902741">I would like to ask the clerk to explain where we are at this point. We had an amendment and a subamendment, and I believe we need to consider the subamendment at this time.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141785">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="318903" Type="27">The Clerk</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902742">At this time, the Standing Committee on Official Languages must vote on Mr. Godin’s subamendment, which seeks to replace the reference to online broadcasters such as Netflix and Amazon Prime, among others, with a reference to online broadcasters of French-language content.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902743">Then we will return to Mr. Deschênes‑Thériault’s amendment, amended or not, depending on the committee’s decision. After that, there may be other subamendments.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141786">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902744">I therefore propose that we dispose of this subamendment by adopting it or not. If members wish to propose further subamendments afterwards, they may do so.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902745">Ms. Chenette, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141788">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319661" Type="47">Madeleine Chenette</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902746">Thank you, Mr. Chair. I didn’t know it was a subamendment. I’m learning something new.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902747">Mr. Godin, I would just like to clarify the concept of “online broadcasters of French-language content.” Does this refer only to broadcasters that air exclusively French-language content? Would it be better to refer to online broadcasters that offer French-language content, as is the case with Cogeco?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902748">I don’t know if you can amend your subamendment.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141796">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902749">Mr. Chair, that is exactly what I meant. I would like to amend my subamendment as suggested by Ms. Chenette, because it is very important to make that distinction. It will be up to the parties to decide which witnesses they want to hear. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141799">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902750">I will try to summarize the situation, and our clerk can help me if I am mistaken.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902751">We are discussing the first part of the amendment presented by Mr. Deschênes‑Thériault, which aims to invite broadcasters such as Netflix or Amazon Prime. Mr. Godin's subamendment proposes instead to invite online broadcasters of French-language content. If the subamendment is adopted, this is how the first part of Mr. Deschênes‑Thériault's amendment would then be worded.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902752">If we want to add what you are proposing, Ms. Chenette, we must first adopt Mr. Godin's subamendment and then propose a new subamendment. Another possibility would be to reject the subamendment and then adopt another one. Either way, we must follow the rules.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902753">Mr. Godin, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141819">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902754">Mr. Chair, I propose that you ask if there is unanimous consent to withdraw my subamendment so that Ms. Chenette can move hers. </ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141823">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902755">Is it the will of the committee to withdraw the subamendment?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902756">
                <B>Some hon. members:</B> Agreed.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902757">(Subamendment withdrawn)</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13147060">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902758">Are there any other subamendments?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141825">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319661" Type="47">Madeleine Chenette</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902759">Mr. Chair, I move instead that we invite “online broadcasters with French-language content.”</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="05">(1205)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141835">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902760">I will ask the clerk to read the first part of Mr. Deschênes‑Thériault's amendment as amended by Ms. Chenette's subamendment.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141838">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="318903" Type="27">The Clerk</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902761">This part, as amended, would end with “online broadcasters with French-language content.”</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141840">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902762">Does everyone agree with this subamendment?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902763">(Subamendment agreed to [<I>See Minutes of Proceedings</I>])</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902764">
                <B>The Chair</B>: We now return to the amended amendment.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902765">Mr. Beaulieu, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141842">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902766">I move another subamendment. I would like the committee to “hold up to two meetings,” because if additional stakeholders are added, it will be difficult to accommodate them all in a single meeting.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13146459">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="47">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902767">Are you proposing to include the words “up to two meetings” or “two meetings”?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13146460">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="47">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902768">We could add the words “two meetings,” but if we are able to have three, we will need to….</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141845">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902769">We should therefore write “at least two meetings,” because otherwise we won't be able to have three.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141846">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902770">Agreed. I move that we write that the committee “hold at least two meetings.”</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141847">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902771">I have consulted with the clerk. First, we need to decide what we want to do with the original amendment. Then, if you wish, you may move a subamendment.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13146462">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="47">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902772">I thought we had adopted it.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141849">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902773">We adopted a subamendment. Now we are discussing the amendment as amended. I will ask the clerk to read back what is being proposed.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141861">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="318903" Type="27">The Clerk</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902774">Thank you, Mr. Chair.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902775">It has been moved that the committee hear at this meeting: (a) broadcasting companies such as Cogeco, Bell, RNC, and Leclerc Communication; (b) a representative from ADISQ, the Association québécoise de l'industrie du disque, du spectacle et de la vidéo; (c) online broadcasters with French-language content; and (d) broadcasters from the ARC, Alliance des radios communautaires du Canada.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902776">Points (a) and (b) were already there, points (c) and (d) have been added.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141869">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902777">Are we ready to adopt this amendment?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902778">Is there unanimous consent to adopt Mr. Deschênes‑Thériault's amendment, as amended?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902779">(Amendment agreed to [<I>See Minutes of Proceedings</I>])</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13147062">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902780">I now return to you, Mr. Beaulieu.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141873">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902781">I move that we replace “one meeting” with “at least two meetings.”</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902782">Cogeco's proposal has a major impact. We should not reduce the quotas for French-language music, as they are already not being fully respected.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141878">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902783">Are there any comments or discussions on the amendment moved by Mr. Beaulieu?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902784">Are you ready to give unanimous consent?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141882">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902785">I have a flag to raise.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141884">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902786">We should raise flags more often. The committee would be more effective.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13146424">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="47">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902787">I'm not sure it will always work like that.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13146425">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902788">Are we agreed?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902789">(Amendment agreed to [<I>See Minutes of Proceedings</I>])</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13146432">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902790">We must now deal with Mr. Godin's amended motion as a whole, and to make everything clear, I will ask the clerk to read the entire amended motion. Then we will decide whether we want to adopt it in its entirety.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902791">Madam Clerk, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141890">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="318903" Type="27">The Clerk</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902792">Thank you.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902793">The motion reads as follows: That, pursuant to Standing Order 108(3)(f), the Standing Committee on Official Languages hold a two-hour meeting as soon as possible to examine the recent request by Cogeco to reduce quotas for French-language songs as required by the conditions of their broadcasting licence. That as part of this meeting, the committee hear from: (a) broadcasting companies such as Cogeco, Bell, RNC, and Leclerc Communication; (b) a representative of ADISQ, the Association québécoise de l'industrie du disque, du spectacle et de la vidéo; (c) online broadcasters with French-language content; and (d) broadcasters from ARC, the Alliance des radios communautaires du Canada. That the purpose of this meeting be to understand the current situation and to evaluate other potential solutions in order to achieve the objective of halting the decline of French.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="10">(1210)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141906">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902794">Mr. Beaulieu, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141908">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902795">Basically, I don’t think that the concept of “French-language broadcasters” closes the door to other organizations, but could even open it: there is ADISQ and ARC, but there could also be UPA. In fact, I am referring to UDA, the Union des artistes, and not the Union des producteurs agricoles.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141916">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902796">Mr. Chair, I think my colleague’s comment is relevant.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902797">For my part, I interpret this concept in the same way as he does. It does not limit us, and we can go beyond it. In fact, there is only one representative from the arts community, and the companies that make a living from French-language music. So I don’t think this concept limits us.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902798">Madam Clerk, can we call witnesses other than those who have been identified, but who are related to the subject? Can we justify this?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141929">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902799">Colleagues, I am aware of the time we have available. I know we want to finish the meeting, but we will need a few minutes to resolve this issue. Our first option is to spend a few minutes on it now. Our second option is to resolve this issue at another meeting.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141932">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="319660" Type="47">Guillaume Deschênes-Thériault</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902800">Could we amend the motion by adding a point (e) specifying that other stakeholders could be added?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141934">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902801">We are moving quickly, but I propose a subamendment specifying that there are no restrictions on the choice of guests. This would protect us. If, for example, we invite a representative from the Union des producteurs agricoles, people could judge the relevance of such a choice. The example is easy, but I think we are all responsible.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141939">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902802">Mr. Godin has moved a subamendment.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141941">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902803">I don’t know how to word this subamendment. Should we use the term “without restrictions”?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141948">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902804">We could just add the words “and other representatives,” which would mean the same thing.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141951">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="318903" Type="27">The Clerk</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902805">Point (d) concerns broadcasters from the Alliance des radios communautaires du Canada. We could add “and other stakeholders in the field.”</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13146442">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="47">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902806">That’s fine.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141953">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902807">We will now vote on this subamendment.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902808">(Subamendment agreed to [<I>See Minutes of Proceedings</I>])</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13146443">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902809">We must now adopt Mr. Godin’s entire motion as amended. Does the Clerk need to read it back?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902810">
                <B>Some hon. members</B>: No.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902811">
                <B>The Chair</B> Do you agree to adopt the motion?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902812">(Motion agreed to [<I>See Minutes of Proceedings</I>])</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Debate" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13146445">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902813">Are there any other matters we should discuss?</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902814">Mr. Godin, you have the floor.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141956">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320673" Type="40">Joël Godin</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902815">That’s what happens when you want to go fast.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902816">Do we have any indication of the topic that will be discussed next Thursday?</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141958">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902817">The subcommittee’s report will dictate our work. The first item in this report is our study on the education continuum.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902818">Given the time and the fact that we want to conclude this meeting, I would ask the clerk to send you all a schedule so that you can see what she is planning. If there are any concerns, we can discuss them at future meetings.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Timestamp Hr="12" Mn="15">(1215)</Timestamp>
          <Intervention Type="" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141963">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320672" Type="40">Mario Beaulieu</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902819">A consultation is currently under way at the Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission. I don’t know if it’s possible, but perhaps the analyst or the clerk could check to see if this consultation is ending soon. I think everyone agrees that the process should be fairly quick. We could then invite the people who are listed, and move on to other business. The analyst and the clerk will see what’s going on. We’ll give them some leeway.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141966">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="318903" Type="27">The Clerk</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902820">We will get back to you on this matter.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
          <Intervention Type="Interjection" ToC="No" ToCText="" id="13141968">
            <PersonSpeaking>
              <Affiliation DbId="320671" Type="35">The Chair</Affiliation>: </PersonSpeaking>
            <Content>
              <ParaText id="8902821">Thank you.</ParaText>
              <ParaText id="8902822">The meeting is adjourned.</ParaText>
            </Content>
          </Intervention>
        </SubjectOfBusinessContent>
      </SubjectOfBusiness>
    </OrderOfBusiness>
  </HansardBody>
</Hansard>